<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The delights of Holland: or, A three months travel about that and the other provinces With observations and reflections on their trade, wealth, strength, beauty, policy, &amp;c. together with a catalogue of the rarities in the anatomical school at Leyden. By William Mountague, Esq;</title>
            <author>Mountague, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 124 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829099</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1973:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The delights of Holland: or, A three months travel about that and the other provinces With observations and reflections on their trade, wealth, strength, beauty, policy, &amp;c. together with a catalogue of the rarities in the anatomical school at Leyden. By William Mountague, Esq;</title>
                  <author>Mountague, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 238, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Sturton, near Serjeant's-Inn Gate, in Chancery -Lane; and A. Bosvile, at the Dial over-against St. Dunstan's Church, in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Goldsmiths' Library, Univeristy of London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:1"/>
            <p>THE DELIGHTS OF <hi>Holland:</hi> OR, A Three Months Travel about that and the other PROVINCES.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>Obſervations</hi> and <hi>Reflections</hi> on their
<hi>Trade, Wealth, Strength, Beauty, Policy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Together with A <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the Rarities in the
<hi>Anatomical School</hi> at <hi>LEYDEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Mountague,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Sturton,</hi> near
<hi>Serjeant's-Inn Gate,</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane;</hi> and <hi>A. Boſvile,</hi> at the <hi>Dial</hi> over-againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church, in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent You <hi>(Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> with a more Exact and Particular Account of <hi>Holland,</hi> and the other <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> about which We Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd, than was ever yet in Print.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:3"/>
            <p>Nothing of Moment eſcap'd our Remark, the moſt Minute (if worthy our Sight and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation) was collected, and digeſted.</p>
            <p>We were Three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, all of a Piece, when We ſet out, We ſpar'd no Coſt of <hi>Time,</hi> or <hi>Money;</hi> We were not Sneaking, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant, but thriftily Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral, rather than Profuſe; We ſtood in the beſt and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Light; that is, We kept the beſt Company, din'd at the principal Ordinaries, (where the greateſt Men of thoſe Countries think it no Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution <pb facs="tcp:33535:3"/>to be preſent,) avoided (as much as with Decency We cou'd) the Converſation of our own Country-Men, Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Gaming; being wholly Intent upon the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs We came about,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Viewing and nicely Prying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Wealth, Strength, Beauty,</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of theſe <hi>Provinces;</hi> never throughly known, or narrowly examin'd into by any of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Nations; at leaſt by what has appear'd in Publick of them.</p>
            <p>I have not obſerv'd any great Order or Method, in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalling <pb facs="tcp:33535:4"/>our <hi>Remarks;</hi> nor do I pretend to
<hi>Stile,</hi> or <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> having contented my ſelf with ſetting down our <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations</hi> as We made them; I have been Faithful and Juſt in the Account and Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Places</hi> and
<hi>Things,</hi> and have omitted nothing Material; I rather choſe a Plain, Intelligent, Familiar, and Manly way of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my ſelf than otherwiſe; and, diſcourſing of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that boaſts much of her Liberty, I have e'en taken a pretty deal my ſelf.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:4"/>
            <p>I have made ſome few <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi> (and thoſe only to open the Eyes of my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to ſee and purſue their <hi>own</hi> true Intereſt,) matter of Fact being what chiefly I aim'd at, and what moſt obliges the Senſible and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my Native Country, has prevail'd upon me to let theſe <hi>Papers</hi> peep abroad; there needs no Apology for them, they will ſpeak for themſelves: They are New, Choice, and very Curious <hi>Obſervations;</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:33535:5"/>if they pleaſe, ſo; if not,
'tis all one to the Collector, for he values neither Frowns or Smiles, Cenſures or Praiſes of this ill-natur'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Age.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33535:5"/>
            <head>THE DELIGHTS OF <hi>Holland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE fourteenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> we took Poſt for
<hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno <hi>1695.</hi>
               </note> where we arriv'd in the Evening; it rain'd from ſeven till two next Morning, ſo that we could not get on board the Pacquet-Boat that Night, but at four the next Morning we embark'd, and were immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under Sail, the Wind very fair, being <hi>Weſt-Nor-Weſt,</hi> it blew a freſh Gale, and continu'd with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33535:6"/>little variation till the next Day when we arriv'd at
<hi>Helovet ſlyice</hi> about eight in the Morning, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had a very good Paſſage, being but twenty eight hours on the Water. We ſtaid here that whole day, which we ſpent in walking up and down and view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fortifications of that Place, which are pretty ſtrong, towards the River, tho' there's a very ſmall Guard kept here; the Water is deep here, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they bring their biggeſt Men of War, which are built at
<hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and lay them up, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a very good Harbor, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others was a Ship of 112 Guns, call'd the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> which was never at Sea, being Crank-ſided, as the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paulins call it; that is, would not bear Sail well. This is a lowſie, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33535:6"/>ſorry Village, and a very cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throat Place, for they make us pay what they pleaſe; but, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
'tis no other than all the Sea-Ports ever did and will do, as well in
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Holland,</hi> tho' here all Places are alike; 'tis a pretty, neat, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built Place, Houſes of Brick, and uniform; here they have Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines of Naval Stores. Our Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet-Boats formerly went to the <hi>Briel,</hi> but now being bigger, of greater force, becauſe of the War, and drawing more Water, they come to this Place, as do the Men of War that convoy his Majeſty to and from <hi>Holland.</hi> We had little to remarque here More than what is mention'd, only a pleaſant Adventure, of a parcel of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen that had never been abroad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33535:7"/>when they firſt came on ſhore here, they went to the beſt Houſe for Accomodation, and immediately fell to kiſſing and feeling the Maids, which is not ſo cuſtomary here, as at home, the Servants would not come near 'em, but ſputter'd in <hi>Dutch,</hi> which they underſtood not, the Miſtreſs did ſo too, the mad <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Sparks they ſwore, and huft, they'd be gone out of the Houſe, which they did, but they would not receive them at any other, ſo they came back again, and gave us opportunity to laugh at 'em; we told them their Frolicks would not go down in this Country. Hence we went by Land to the <hi>Briel</hi> in a Waggon, which is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, and noiſie too, for our Heads were hardly ſettled after <pb n="5" facs="tcp:33535:7"/>the toſſing we had at Sea, where moſt of us clean'd our Stomachs very well, but theſe Waggons rattle and make ſuch a noiſe, that almoſt made our Heads ake; they drive with a pair of Horſes a-breſt, without Harneſs, but in ordinary Geers, and travel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly three mile an hour, not more, nor leſs, which makes them reckon the Diſtances of Places by the Hour, and not by the League, or Mile. This Town lies about half a League from the mouth of the <hi>Maeſe,</hi> (a famous River, like our <hi>Thames</hi>) 'tis well fortified, pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty well peopled, about three thouſand Families, Houſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently well built, Streets well pav'd, cleanly and broad; Canals run through part of it, with rows of Trees on each <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33535:8"/>ſide, pleaſant Meadows lie about it, but the Air is not healthful, being thick and foggy, and too near the Sea. Here was the Foundation of this famous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth laid, for this was the firſt Place that revolted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Spain,</hi> her ancient Lord, in the Year
1572. It is of great Conſequence, having the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of all Ships and Veſſels, in their Paſſage to <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> &amp;c. It was one of the Cautionary Towns put in the Poſſeſſion of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and reſtor'd to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> by King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, her Succeſſor. We ſtaid two Days here, walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and viewing the Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the whole City, which is but ſmall; the Walls are part Brick, part Earth, two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in Circumference; there
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33535:8"/>are ſeveral Pieces of Braſs Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non mounted upon Carriages upon all the Points; four Gates, with two Draw-Bridges to each, and Bulwarks to plant Cannon upon; there has been four Ravelins, and ſome Out-works, but we could ſee but one ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which by the Form we gueſs'd to be ſo, for 'tis out of repair, and ſo is the whole Wall, which, in a War with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> is put into a better Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, with a good Gariſon, but they apprehend no Danger from the <hi>French;</hi> the Land about it produces good Corn, but not much: The People here are leſs Courteous than thoſe that live in the great Trading-Towns, (tho' you are not to expect great Civility from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who pretend not to much breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33535:9"/>ſome ſay, the groſneſs of the Air influences them in their Manners, and that the Moon, who governs them, (<hi>Cancer</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Aſcendent) makes them Clowniſh; but of this there is no certainty; tho' the Sea-men of all Nations are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be as rough, ſurly, and ill-natur'd as the Element they live upon: And if the Water has Influence, why not the Air? Here is a pretty little <hi>Stadt-Houſe,</hi> or
<hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> as we call it in <hi>London,</hi> and a good Church founded <hi>Anno</hi> 1372, by the Counteſs <hi>Matilda</hi> for them, and another Church for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> an Hoſpital for Orphans, a good Market-place, and an old and new Haven. <hi>Rotterdam</hi> has got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the Trade from the <hi>Briel.</hi> About ten in the Forenoon we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33535:9"/>took <hi>Scout</hi> (which is a little Boat with a Sail, and goes every hour, the Bell ringing to give Notice to Paſſengers, as it does in other Places,) for <hi>Maezlandſluyce,</hi> a little Fiſher-Town, a League from the <hi>Briel,</hi> half an Hours ſail with the Wind, an hour and half againſt it; 'tis a pleaſant Place; they have within theſe few Years built a very good Church there; before this Place lie a great many
<hi>Buſſes,</hi> or Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Veſſels, which is their chief Trade, and by which they don't only live, but grow rich, as we in <hi>England</hi> might do, if we were not infatuated; moſt of their <hi>Buſſes</hi> were gone out to Sea, to catch Herrings on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſt, becauſe the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> are ſo lazy they won't catch 'em themſelves. About half Seas <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33535:10"/>over we were met by ſome Friends of ours,
<hi>Dutch</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who came from <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> on purpoſe to receive us, which they did with all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of Love and Joy; we went a-ſhore together, and got to the beſt Houſe, and fell abord the pickled Herring, which was extraordinary good; we made 'em ſwim in Rheniſh Wine, of which we let down a good quantity. Here we hir'd a Waggon to carry us to <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam,</hi> which in our way we paſt through.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAERDINGEN,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ulaer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingen.</note> a League off, a ſmall Village, a Fiſher-Place, 'twas anciently a City, and well fortified, but ruin'd by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo near the River <hi>Maeſe,</hi> which broke in upon it. A League further lies <hi>Schedam,</hi> a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33535:10"/>ſmall City, which has a Vote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the
<hi>States,</hi> and is call'd the <hi>Oldeſt, Boldeſt, Wiſeſt,</hi> and was the <hi>Richeſt</hi> in ancient Times, wonderfully Couragious were the Inhabitants againſt the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards;</hi> now famous for the Fiſhery, and making of Nets to catch Fiſh. Three or four
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Miles further along the ſame River lies
<hi>Delphs-howen,</hi> a ſmall Town, nothing but Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Marriners live here: This Place, with ſmall Charge, might be made impregnable, (as may many others in this Country) by reaſon of its ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion near ſo much Water.</p>
            <p>Half a League from hence is <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> a great, ſtrong, fine,<note place="margin">Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> and very rich City, one of the moſt celebrated Ports of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Second for Trade in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33535:11"/>lying very commodiouſly upon the River
<hi>Maeſe,</hi> has great Commerce with <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> (when in Peace) and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and is much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in great and ſmall Fiſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a very flouriſhing Place: Here are divers Canals cut, which are ſo well contriv'd and kept, that the greateſt Ships can enter, and there lie ſecurely; and ſome Ships of two and three hundred Tuns are brought up into the middle of the Town, where the Goods are deliver'd at the Merchants Doors, which is a very great conveniency. <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> the greateſt Reſtorer of Learning, was born in this City <hi>Anno Dom.</hi>
1467, he died in <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> in <hi>Alſatia:</hi> Remarkable was the Gratitude of this People, who to preſerve his Name and <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33535:11"/>Memory, have at their Charge ſet up his Effigies in Braſs, well done, with a great Book in his Hand (the Leaves of which he turns over as oft as he hears the Clock ſtrike, which forſooth is a Piece of <hi>Dutch</hi> Wit.) This Statue was erected, as they told us, in 1564, and roughly handled by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in 1572. 'tis now rail'd in with Iron. This City is now wholly at the Devotion of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (now our King) the People being paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and zealous Lovers of his Perſon and Intereſt, which they expreſs to the higheſt upon all Occaſions. Here they brew good Beer, which is ſent to the Cities and Villages all round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; they alſo ſerve the <hi>States</hi> Armies and Navies with it. Turf and Wood is their firing, the <pb n="14" facs="tcp:33535:12"/>firſt is cheap, the ſecond dear, and is burnt by the better ſort only. As we came near any of their Towns we diſtinguiſh'd an odd ſmell, which comes from the Turf, and is unpleaſant, and we believe unwholſom; 'tis ſtronger than that of
<hi>New-Caſtle</hi> Coal in <hi>London.</hi> Theſe People are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally more obliging to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> than in any other Place, which is to be wholly attributed to their frequent Converſation, and Dealing with them. Here they build very great Ships of War, of a hundred Guns, and downward. We went on bord ſome of the biggeſt, and view'd them well within, and without; they are not ſo cleaverly and neatly built as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> nor ſo fit for Accomodation, but more clumſie, but then very <pb n="15" facs="tcp:33535:12"/>ſtrong, and ſit for Service, plain Paint, and without any Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and very little Carving, which is a ſuperfluous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Expence; and which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> were once very vain in, tho' 'tis now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt worn out of Practice, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Guilding, which may be proper for Yachts and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure-Boats, but not for Men of War. We ſaw their
<hi>Stadt-Houſe</hi> or <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> which is a very good Building, and Saint <hi>Lawrence</hi>'s Church, which is a great one, in it a very large old Organ, the <hi>Dutch Presbyterians</hi> being not ſo nice and ſqueemiſh as the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Uſe of that Muſick in Churches: In this Church are the Monuments of ſeveral great Sea-Commanders. The <hi>Engliſh, <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33535:13"/>Scotch,</hi> and
<hi>French,</hi> have alſo each a Church here. Here is an open Place for the Merchants to meet in, which they call the <hi>Exchange,</hi> but no noble Piazza's to ſecure 'em from the Weather, as at <hi>London.</hi> We ſtaid here ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Days, and ſometimes din'd at the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſometimes at the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Houſes. The Ordinaries are the beſt and cheapeſt Places to eat at, for then you know your Expence, which otherwiſe is at the VVill and Pleaſure of your Landlord, who Arbitrarily impoſes upon you; and this without redreſs, for if you complain to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, he will give it againſt you, and you muſt pay it; they know you are led by Curioſity to paſs through, to view their Country, not to live in it, and <pb n="17" facs="tcp:33535:13"/>you muſt contribute to the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it. The <hi>Dutch</hi> are ill Cooks, and verifie the Proverb,
<hi>That God ſends Meat, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil the Dreſſer.</hi> They have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Soupes and Slops, very inſipid, they roaſt and boil all to Rags, ſo that you don't know what ſort of Fleſh 'tis when it comes to the Table. The <hi>French</hi> err a little on that ſide, but then they make ſome amends with their Sawces, which are tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, tho' hardly wholſome; that being the beſt Diet, which is the ſimpleſt and moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Nature; ſo that we all agreed in this, That the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> way of Boiling, Roaſting, and Broiling, with preſerving the Gravy, (which is the beſt Sawce) is the beſt in the World.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33535:14"/>
            <p>To <hi>DELFT</hi> we went next,<note place="margin">Delft.</note> betwixt which Place and <hi>Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> is a great Magazine of Gun-Powder for the <hi>States</hi> Service, 'tis a well-built Brick Houſe with a Draw-Bridge, and a Moat all round it, which is wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, that if it ſhould by any Accident (which ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens) blow up, it cannot do any other Damage; for 'tis dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to lodge great Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines (as in the
<hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi>) near great and populous Cities. This very City of <hi>Delft</hi> was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly ſhatter'd by the blowing up of the great Magazine of Powder kept there <hi>Anno</hi> 1654, which occaſion'd the building the aforeſaid Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delft</hi> is a fair and populous City, very clean, well built, and very pleaſant; well ſeated in a <pb n="19" facs="tcp:33535:14"/>Plain of Meadows, which may be laid all round under Water, if they open their Sluces, when the Wind is Eaſt-North-Eaſt. At the Entrance of it ſtands a general Magazine of Warlike Stores (but no Powder) for the Publick Service. This City was burnt to Aſhes <hi>Anno</hi> 1536, but ſoon re-built, and now in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Glory than ever. The <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company of this Place have here a very good Houſe and large Ware-Houſes; as alſo an eighth part of the Great or General Stock, this being the Third Town of <hi>Holland,</hi> having the Third Voice in the <hi>States,</hi> whither it ſends Deputies, as alſo to all the other Colleges. Here are very fine Buildings, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the Town-Houſe, with theſe two Verſes on the Front.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33535:15"/>
            <q>
               <l>Haec domus odit, amat, punit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervat, honorat,</l>
               <l>Nequitiam, Pacem, Crimina, Jura, Probos.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Here is a ſpacious Market-Place between this Houſe and the great Church, in which ſtands <hi>William</hi> the Firſt Prince of
<hi>Orange</hi> (Great Grand-Father to his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty King
<hi>William</hi>) at full length, in Armor, in Copper Effigie; at each corner of this Monument ſtands <hi>Juſtice, Prudence, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and
<hi>Valour,</hi> all in Copper, and very large; and beſides this, the Prince lies at length in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, with a Dog (having had his Life once ſav'd by a Dog) at his Feet, all under Marble Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramids: 'Tis the moſt Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Tomb in all the <hi>Seventeen <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33535:15"/>Provinces.</hi> Here that Prince kept his Court, and here was that brave Prince aſſaſſinated in the
51ſt Year of his Age, being ſhot by a Piſtol with three Bullets, as he roſe from the Table, by one <hi>Balthazar Gerrard,</hi> a
<hi>Burgundian,</hi> ſo that he died without having time to ſay any more than, <hi>Lord have Mercy on my Soul and this poor People.</hi> The Murderer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and Son of one who had ſuffer'd for his Religion; by which he inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf into the Prince's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, who employ'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted him in Buſineſs of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: The Villain never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to get off, but was taken and pinch'd to death with hot Irons, his Fleſh being firſt ſlaſh'd with a Knife, and ſo Piece by Piece torn off with hot Pincers; <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33535:16"/>he died obſtinate, and ſaid,
<hi>If it were to do again, he would do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the t'other Church is a Monument of Admiral <hi>Trump</hi>'s, inrich'd with Miniature, and a fine Inſcription: 'Tis a ſtately one, with the Arms of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hanging in Frames over it: 'Twas erected at the
<hi>States</hi> Charge, in acknowledgment, for the good Service he did his Country.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Church is <hi>Myn Heer Pithin</hi>'s Tomb, a very handſome one: He was a <hi>Dutch</hi> Admiral, and took the Plate-Fleet from the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The Churches here, and in all the Seven
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces,</hi> are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally bigger than ours in
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> but fewer in Number.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33535:16"/>
            <p>Here is a large and neat Market, or Fleſh-Hall (as they call it) for all ſorts of Butchers Meat, which they have very good, and in great plenty, and not dear truly; which I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention, becauſe they who have not travell'd, upbraid the <hi>Dutch</hi> with living upon Onions, Roots, Herb, Milk, and pickled Herrings, and ſay, they have no Fleſh, and rarely eat any; 'tis true, they aae ſparing, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'tis the better for their Health; for the devouring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Fleſh muſt needs fill our Bodies with many hot and groſs Humours, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently impair our Health. They have alſo a good Fiſh-Market here, and another of Fruits, Roots, and Herbs.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33535:17"/>
            <p>The People in this City are rich, trade much to Sea, and make much Porcelain, or fine Earthen Wares, to a great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, tho' far ſhort of
<hi>China,</hi> which they pretend to reſemble, and brew good Beer here; but the Remark we made in general of their Beer (of which they have many ſorts, as <hi>Rotterdam</hi> Beer, <hi>Dort, Engliſh</hi> Beer, white Beer, ſweet Beer, <hi>Breda</hi> Beer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is, That tho' they have an Art of refining it, ſo that it looks (ſome of it) very clear, yet it taſtes inſipid, and indeed is but weak, compar'd to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> having little or no reliſh of the Mault.</p>
            <p>From hence we went to the <hi>Hague,</hi> which is three Miles, or an Hour farther, a Village, as 'tis generally call'd, but a very
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33535:17"/>beautiful one, the fineſt in the World, agreed by all Travellers: The very <hi>Italians</hi> themſelves confeſs it, who may juſtly boaſt of the beſt Buildings in the World, tho' there are ſome of that Nation that chuſe to live here rather than at home, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>this is the pleaſanteſt Place in the World;</hi> tho' we muſt own we are not altogether of their Opinion. It is certainly the fineſt Village in
<hi>Europe,</hi> and much exceeding many Cities in Bigneſs, and Beauty. In this Place it was that the <hi>States</hi> by their Edict <hi>Anno</hi> 1586, abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Authority of <hi>Philip</hi> the Second King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and held a Conference upon the Five Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Remonſtrants,
<hi>An.</hi> 1610, which brought about the calling of the Synod of
<hi>Dort,</hi> 
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33535:18"/>ſo fam'd in Story. The Princes of
<hi>Orange</hi> us'd to keep their Courts here, till the preſent Prince
<hi>William</hi> aſcended the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne. The Earls of
<hi>Holland</hi> had their Reſidence here, and founded the Prince's Houſe, which is a good old Brick-Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with a Court before it, for the Foot-Guards to draw up in, and lodge or ground their Arms in. Here the States General, the States Provincial, the Court of <hi>Holland,</hi> the High-Council Court of <hi>Brabrant,</hi> and the Council of State aſſemble; but that Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which deſerves moſt Notice, and a particular Deſcription, is where the States of <hi>Holland</hi> meet, which is indeed a very fine, ſpacious, lofty Room, with very fine Hangings round, which touch the very Cieling, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33535:18"/>with their Arms curiouſly wove in them, made on purpoſe for them; ſome People of moſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are alſo wove in theſe Hangings, as if looking over Galleries; which, when the Room is a little darkned, which is done by the Servant that ſhows it, the better to repreſent it, appears as if they were all alive, nodding of their Heads and talking to one another. The Cieling it ſelf is painted very finely, by an
<hi>Italian</hi> Maſter; as alſo the Two Chimney-Pieces, in which are repreſented Peace and War, very curiouſly; the firſt is <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> a very beautiful Woman, with a pure white Dove on her Lap, with other Emblems of Peace about her; the ſecond is <hi>Mars,</hi> or a Soldier compleatly armed, with a Plume of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33535:19"/>on his Head-piece, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling on a great open Book, all bloody, on which is writ in large Letter,
<hi>PRIVELEGIA.</hi> The Seats are all rail'd in; that of the Princes, is an Elbow-chair at the upper-end of the Table; about which (on Chairs with Backs) ſits the Knighthood of <hi>Holland,</hi> who have but one Vote, which each City that ſends De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties has; and at the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end ſits the Penſioner, who is Keeper of the Great Seal and Secretary, as they told us, before whom lies a ſmall wooden Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which when he knocks with, is that their Debates ceaſe, and they be ſilent. The Seats of the Deputies of the ſeveral Cities are on Benches, or Forms; every Seat has a Cuſhion of green Cloth, (with which the Seats <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33535:19"/>and Table is cover'd) with the Arms of that City or Town on it, for which they ſerve, or which they repreſent: At the upper-end of this noble Room, on each ſide of that Chimney, is a diſtinct Place for the two Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries, on which lie great Books, to take the Minutes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces</hi> are ſo call'd, from their Union at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht, Anno</hi> 1579. They are commonly (but confuſedly and improperly) all call'd <hi>Holland,</hi> that being the richeſt and moſt populous Province of them all, and indeed worth them all, and therefore for its Excellency it ſwallows up in its Name the t'other ſix; and, indeed, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the charge of the War, and the ſupport of the State, and the preſervation of <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33535:20"/>their Lands from the Sea, by vaſt and expenſive Dykes, or Banks, far beyond what all the other do, put together; of a Hundred <hi>Livers,</hi> it pays Fifty nine and a half, which is very conſiderable; but then it is the great Trading Province. Theſe Provinces, which before own'd Subjection to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and were wonderfully Loyal to their Prince, Lovers of his Perſon, and Zealous for his Intereſt, till he fell in upon their Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their Religious and Civil Rights, have ſince been Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of one another, or to ſpeak ſtrictly and more properly, are Seven Commonwealths, which altogether now make but one, under the Name of, <hi>The States General of the</hi> United-Provinces <hi>of the</hi> Low-Countries: The Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33535:20"/>of this Republick reſiding in the States General, but the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority in and over all Things reſerv'd, by reaſon of the Alliance, has remained in the States of each Province; and this is that which they call the <hi>Sovereignty.</hi> The Seal of this formidable Commonwealth is a <hi>Lion,</hi> holding a bundle of ſeven bound Arrows, alluding to as many confederated Provinces. There is no State in being, of ſo ſmall an extent, which has ſo great a Number of Fortreſſes, and which ſeems better defended by the Nature of the Places than this. It has the Sea, and ſeveral Rivers to ſecure it: The <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Maeſe,</hi> the
<hi>Waal,</hi> and the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</hi> Of theſe ſeven
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> there are four towards the Weſt, <hi>Holland, Zealand, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht,</hi> 
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:33535:21"/>and <hi>Guelderland;</hi> three towards the Eaſt, <hi>Over-Yſſel, Frieſland,</hi> and
<hi>Groninghen.</hi> In their Aſſemblies, the Provinces thus give their Votes, <hi>Guelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> firſt of all, then <hi>Holland, Zealand, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht, Frieſland, Over-Yſſel,</hi> laſt <hi>Groninghen.</hi> Each of 'em ſends its Deputies to this Place, (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Hague</hi>) where are form'd three Colleges, or Aſſemblies of them; the States General, the Council of State, and the Chamber of Accompts. In the Aſſemblies of the States General, all the Provinces above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd muſt conſent, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and in particular, to the Reſolutions that are taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and do not follow the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Voices. Each Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince may ſend thither one, two, three, four, or five Deputies, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33535:21"/>but all theſe Deputies have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether but one Voice, and have right to preſide therein but one Week: That of <hi>Guelderland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, becauſe it is the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and its Plenipotentiaries were the firſt who propos'd the Union. This Province, <hi>Anno</hi> 1674, offer'd the Sovereignty to the Prince of
<hi>Orange</hi> (now King of <hi>England,</hi>) it being the time the
<hi>French</hi> King invaded them with mighty Armies, which like a Torrent over-run all, and made ſuch ſurpriſing Conqueſts, that in a very ſhort time they reduced three Provinces, and between fifty and ſixty conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Towns; but their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs was ſtopt, and they repell'd by the Bravery and Conduct of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who new modell'd the States Armies, and <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33535:22"/>from raw, inexpert, and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciplin'd Soldiers, and bad Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, (rais'd by the Favour and Intereſt of the Burgo-Maſters and Principal Magiſtrates) made them very formidable to their Enemies, and ſnatch'd the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels from the greateſt Generals of the Age, at the Head of the beſt Troops, and recover'd part of their Loſſes, and had the reſt reſign'd by the Peace <hi>Anno</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>The Admiralty has five Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (and as many Magazines,) which are thoſe of <hi>Rotterdam, Amſterdam, Enkuyſen, Midleburg,</hi> and <hi>Harlingen:</hi> The three firſt in <hi>Holland,</hi> the fourth in
<hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the fifth in <hi>Frieſland.</hi> The whole Care and Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe ſeveral Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is committed to Men of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33535:22"/>great Ability and Integrity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in Maritime Affairs, and of great Experience in Matters relating to their Office,
<hi>viz.</hi> building of Ships, buying of Stores and Naval Proviſions, equipping ſingle Ships, Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, or Fleets appointing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voys,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Officers, as indeed all others, throughout their whole Government, have but ſmall Penſions or Salaries, the <hi>States</hi> being very ſparing of the Publick Monies; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Servants and Miniſters of this Commonwealth live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, that is, are prudent and thrifty in the Management of their private Fortune, modeſt and plain in their Habit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Pomp of Coaches, or great Trains, or large Houſes, or coſtly feeding, or high drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <pb n="36" facs="tcp:33535:23"/>complying with the cuſtom of their Country, and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves with ſimple Diet; no Fricaſſee's, Ragou's, or Gril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liades, but a good Diſh of Cabil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liau, Cod-Fiſh, of which the <hi>Dutch</hi> in general are great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers. There ſeems to be a natural and habitual Probity amongſt the Officers of this State.</p>
            <p>Here are ſome Remains of their ancient Nobility, ſome Branches of the <hi>Bredreodes,</hi> the <hi>Waſſenaers,</hi> and the
<hi>Egmonts;</hi> this Nobility has ever voted there the firſt, tho' (as I ſaid before) it has but one Voice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, whereas the Eighteen Cities of the ſame Provinces, have there each one, with the Sovereignty bound by Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33535:23"/>
            <p>Moſt of the Towns in this Province are beautiful and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, having been built in the laſt Age.</p>
            <p>Fronting the Prince's Houſe ſtands a great Hall, reſembling (tho' not ſo big as) <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> full (like that) of Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, and Toy-Shops. Here is kept (in a Chamber at the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end) the High Court of Juſtice, from which no Appeals are granted, and to which all are made. The Civil or <hi>Roman</hi> Law is in practiſe all over theſe Countries. This Village has no Vote among the <hi>States,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
'tis a Village, for there are ſeveral Cities have no Votes, but becauſe they did not ſend De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> when the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was upon the Anvil.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33535:24"/>
            <p>The <hi>Hague</hi> paies more Exciſe for Wine and other Liquors, than <hi>Amſterdam, Rotterdam,</hi> and <hi>Dort,</hi> three great Cities, put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as they told us; and it has the face of Truth, for here is the great concourſe of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, Nobility, Gentry, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Embaſſadors, Envoys, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now, (and for ſome Years paſt) of the <hi>Congreſs,</hi> theſe are the Wine-Bibbers, for the common
<hi>Dutch</hi> are ſatisfied with a ſopie of Brandy-Wine, a Dram of that Liquor does their Buſineſs better, it keeps out the Cold and the Fogs, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens them, and makes them fitter for Action; and, indeed, they ſeem to have ſome occaſion for it, for they are naturally ſlow and heavy, but then very dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and conſtant, elſe 'twould <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33535:24"/>have been impoſſible to have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd ſuch great Works as they to their Honour, and the Safety of their Country have happily atchiev'd. And indeed ſtrong and ſpirituous Liquors ſeem to me to be more neceſſary for, as well as natural to this Nation, conducing mightily to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their Health, which muſt needs be fluctuating, where the Air is ſo foul: Their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is a Bog, a Marſh, full of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours and Fogs, which are Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and Sulphureous, and ſend forth unpleaſant and unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Scents; and therefore their frequent Tippling ought not to be charg'd on them as a Crime, eſpecially by a Neighbour-Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) who have a better Country, and a better Air, and are in their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33535:25"/>more lively, brisk, and pert, having more Heat, more Fire within, are as Cholerick as the t'other Flegmatick, drudge not like them, therefore want not the like Supports, being lazy and idle People, chuſing rather (ſome of 'em) to ſtarve than work. Beſides, they Bumper it but ſeldom, and at ſet, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſolemn Occaſions, and then forbear a good while, or at leaſt ſome time, but my <hi>Country-men,</hi> to their ſhame, are always Sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Drunkening, toiling at it, and valuing themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on making one another Drunk; indeed, 'tis a noble Atchievement to Fuddle the whole <hi>Company:</hi> 'Tis a glorious <hi>Conqueſt</hi> to leave 'em all ſlain upon the Floor, (as they call it.) Now the bearing of much ſtrong Liquor is an <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33535:25"/>argument of a thick Skull ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than otherwiſe, which I find few very fond of, at leaſt none would have it if they could help it.</p>
            <p>In the Afternoon we hired a Coach, a very genteel one, and the Coach-Man in a good Habit, of grey, reſembling a Livery, with a pair of handſom, fat, well-kept Horſes; we agreed with him to wait upon us the whole Afternoon, which he did, for about Eight Shillings Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and firſt carried us to the Prince's Houſe in the <hi>Boſch</hi> or Wood, about two Miles from the <hi>Hague;</hi> 'tis a very pretty well-built (tho' old) Box, (as we call ſmall Seats in <hi>England</hi>) with good Gardens, tho' not now very well kept; at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of this Houſe ſtand Four
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33535:26"/>whole Marble Effigies of <hi>William</hi> the Firſt,
<hi>Maurice</hi> his Brother, <hi>Henry,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> the Second, (the preſent King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi>'s Father,) all Princes of
<hi>Orange,</hi> very curiouſly done. Directly forwards is a lofty, well-painted, well-guilt, well-floor'd ſmall Hall, with a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery for Muſick all round the top of it, and three or four ſmall lodging Rooms below, and ſeveral very good ones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, one Cloſet of all true
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Japan, made of Cabinets or Cheſts taken in pieces; 'tis three Yards long, and one and a half broad. The Wall and Cielings all round beautified with curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paintings, repreſenting the Actions of <hi>Frederick Henry,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Wood in which this little Houſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33535:26"/>(fit only for Banqueting, or a Supper in the cool of a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer's Evening, or, indeed, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat with a Miſtreſs) ſtands is very pleaſant, and with coſt might be made much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful. There is a pretty deal of Ground about it, and well wooded, but has no Deer, or any other Game.</p>
            <p>As we came back we rid by the <hi>Mall</hi> or <hi>Mell,</hi> much like that in St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park,</hi> but not ſo neat, or well kept, being not ſo much frequented. Then we were drove back through part of the <hi>Hague</hi> to <hi>Schevelin,</hi> (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a fine ſmooth way, pav'd all with Bricks, and planted on each ſide with Trees, to make it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, which was done at vaſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, being before all ſandy Hills,) a little Village about two <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33535:27"/>Miles from thence, fam'd in Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Embarkation of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> when he went to take Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Three Crowns, from which he had been long kept by the Uſurper <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi> 'Tis a little Fiſher-Place; we rid along the ſhoar two or three Hours, in view of the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an or Main-Sea, where we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſome Wrecks on that Coaſt.</p>
            <p>Between <hi>Schevelin</hi> and the <hi>Hague</hi> is a Houſe of
<hi>Myn Heer Bentink</hi>'s, (now Earl of <hi>Portland</hi>) it is but an ordinary old Piece of Building, tho' his Lordſhip has lately added ſome new Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to it, but the Gardens are new and very extraordinary; there is a very fine Orangerie, and a new well-built Room or <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33535:27"/>Green-houſe to preſerve them in Winter, and in the middle and at each end a great Stove, in which great Fires are kept du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the extreme cold Weather. In the middle of the new Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is a fine Oval Fountain. The Garden is made up like a Half-Moon, full of fine Flower-Pots: In the old Garden is a neat Aviary, and a ſmall Moat with Fowl in it, fine Walks and Figures, and a Summer-Houſe built upon an Artificial Rock.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Principal Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the <hi>Hague,</hi> the Houſe built by Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> claims the firſt Rank, for 'tis a ſtately One, of Modern Structure. Here <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of
<hi>Great Britain,</hi> was lodged and treated by the <hi>States</hi> when his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33535:28"/>Majeſty came from <hi>Breda</hi> to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark for
<hi>England, Anno</hi> 1660. The Dukes of <hi>Brandenburg, Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and others of the Illuſtrious <hi>German</hi> Princes, when they come to the
<hi>Hague</hi> on Viſit, or Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are conducted hither, and remain here during their ſtay. In this Houſe are the Pictures of moſt of the
<hi>European</hi> Kings, and a great many <hi>American</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. In the Years 1672 and 1673, the Inhabitants were in great Pain leſt the
<hi>French,</hi> who were then very near them, ſhou'd have made 'em a Viſit, becauſe there's no Fortifications, only a Ditch of Water: The Trees round about it were order'd to be cut down, to impede the <hi>French</hi> in their march, who, like very civil Gentlemen, came not to give them the leaſt Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance; <pb n="47" facs="tcp:33535:28"/>young Trees are ſince planted in the room of the old. The Confuſion then was ſuch, that they ſent ſeveral Waggons laden with Money, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Accompts, to be ſecur'd in the
<hi>Stadt-Houſe</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And much about this time was the fatal and ſudden Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy acted on the two unhappy Brothers, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Cornelis de Wit;</hi> the one ſaid to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt States-man in the World; the other an Admiral, who had alſo ſerv'd in an eminent Poſt in the Civil Government. The Populace roſe and cut them both in Pieces, without ſuffering them to ſpeak one Word for themſelves; they always oppos'd the Intereſt of the Houſe of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> which was the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of their State, to which <pb n="48" facs="tcp:33535:29"/>they were believ'd to be Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: And thus fell
<hi>John de Wit,</hi> who was allow'd by all to have been a very extraordinary Man, after a long Adminiſtration of the great and principal Affairs of this Republick.</p>
            <p>Here are a great many <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, French, Scots, Germans,</hi> and ſome of moſt Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> but more <hi>Germans</hi> and
<hi>French</hi> than any.</p>
            <p>Near the Town ſtands an Iron Cage (ſeldom us'd) in which are put notorious Criminals, to be expos'd to the Scorn and Contempt of the Rabble.</p>
            <p>We went to the new Church, built not many Years ſince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very Spot where the common Bawdy-Houſes ſtood, which were pull'd down to make way for this noble Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture: <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33535:29"/>A happy Converſion! Houſes of Filth and Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs turn'd into a Houſe of Prayer! 'Tis adorn'd with Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers Arms, and Eſcutcheons of the Nobility and Gentry. They call it an Oval Building, but I think it almoſt round; it has no Pillars within, ſo that all the People may ſee as well as hear the Miniſter: 'Tis a large Church, and as they told us, there is not ſo fine a one in all the
<hi>Seventeen Pronvinces;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind it is the Rag-ſtreet, where there is kept a great Rag-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket; abundance of Money is got by buying and ſelling that ſort of mean Merchandize.</p>
            <p>We went hence to view the great Church, which is a good old Piece of Building, with a very high ſquare Brick Steeple, <pb n="50" facs="tcp:33535:30"/>ſeen afar off; here is Admiral <hi>Opdam</hi>'s Monument, 'tis very Magnificent; he commanded the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet in an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> he was blown up, Ship and all; he had the Folly and Vanity to carry a Broom in his Main-top; as much as to ſay, he would ſweep the Sea of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but they made a ſhift to ſend him and his Broom to take the Air; he was a bold fighting Fellow, but a Man of no great Conduct.</p>
            <p>Then we were ſhew'd the Cloiſter-Church, which is a large Pile, built <hi>Anno</hi> 1399. And ſo to the <hi>French</hi> Church, which was formerly the Chappel of the Earls of <hi>Holland;</hi> they ſay, 'tis bigger than the <hi>French</hi> Church in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but we thought not ſo.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33535:30"/>
            <p>Here is an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, or Chappel rather, for 'tis a ſmall one, very plain and ordinary. The <hi>Germans</hi> preach there early in the Morning, then the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> who have the <hi>Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> read to 'em; the Auditors are but few, we counted about Seventy. Here are a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fine Buildings, fit for Petty Princes, they are fill'd with Embaſſadors, Envoys, Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hir'd a Coach to carry us to <hi>Honſlayerdyke,</hi> one of King <hi>William</hi>'s Houſes; in our way thither we paſt through
<hi>Ryſwick,</hi> a little Village, with a good Church, a Mile from the
<hi>Hague;</hi> and a little farther another Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, call'd
<hi>Watringe;</hi> as alſo the Seats of many Country Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, pleaſantly ſituated, with <pb n="52" facs="tcp:33535:31"/>long Rows of Trees on each ſide the Walk which leads to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honſlaerdyke</hi> is about eight or nine Miles from the
<hi>Hague,</hi> almoſt the ſame Diſtance as <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> from
<hi>London;</hi> it is a very neat Piece of Building, Founded by <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> the King's Grand-Father, about ſixty or ſeventy Years ago; 'tis a pretty Square, with a Baſs-Court, and very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Moat all round it: King <hi>William</hi> has lately added ſome new Lodgings to it. Here was always a Guard of Horſe and Foot Soldiers without, and
<hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> within Doors, who are luſty ſwinging Fellows, with black frizzing Hair and great Whiskers, they wear flat Caps and Cloaks, and look big and <pb n="53" facs="tcp:33535:31"/>handſomly for a Guard, when the King was here.</p>
            <p>The Gardens that belong to this Houſe are not extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they are well made up and neatly kept; in the middle ſtands a Fountain, eight Leaden gilt Statues, and three or four Stone Images about it. Here are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and long Walks, adorn'd with Trees, which front the Houſe, and make it very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant: Two ſmall Parks with low Pails, and ſhallow Ditches about them; a few Deer; we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd no difference between them and the
<hi>Engliſh;</hi> here are above ten or twelve Couple of Hounds, and a very large Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary with great variety of Birds.</p>
            <p>It was our fortune to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe but ſeldom with the
<hi>Dutch,</hi> tho' many of themſpeak prompt <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33535:32"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> however we engag'd in Diſcourſe with three or four Gentlemen, led by Curioſity to ſee this Houſe, who amongſt other things, told us, as their Obſervation, That we had in <hi>England</hi> (where they ſaid they had been) three ſorts of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min; (we were glad to hear we had no more,) but demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they were, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>Parſons, Phyſicians, and Lawyers, who devour all the good Things of this World;</hi> they told us, they kept their Miniſters in due Bounds, and upon the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, there were none rich, but none poor, they had no Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhopricks, Biſhopricks, Deana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Prebendaries, and fat Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings; the <hi>States</hi> paid their Parſons their Stipend, uſually about One hundred and fifty,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33535:32"/>or two hundred Pounds Sterling <hi>per Annum;</hi> they kept to their Texts, and never meddled with their Affairs of <hi>State,</hi> or any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Matters, but contented themſelves with Admoniſhing the People from their Pulpits to lead good Lives, which they themſelves were good Examples of; no ſawcy Prieſts there, to thruſt their Noſes into, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with other Mens Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; if any of their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers happen'd at any time to make any Sallies of Zeal, and touch the <hi>States</hi> never ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, they had a Staff and a clean pair of Shooes ſent, and were told they muſt troop off.</p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen alſo gave us their Sentiments of the
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Soldiers, they <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33535:33"/>own'd they were both Brave; that the <hi>Scots</hi> wou'd, and the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> wou'd not work; that the firſt cou'd fare hard, but not the t'other; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man muſt be well fed, good pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Beef and Pudding, and good Ale was his fare, and if he had that nothing cou'd wrong him.</p>
            <p>We went to the Place where they caſt Cannon and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars; 'tis a handſome well-built Houſe; there were ſeveral Pieces in the Mold, and a great many newly caſt; as alſo Mortars, all fit for the Field: thence to the Magazine, where they lay up their Cannon, Mortars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the Harneſs and other Tac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle belonging to Carriages and Waggons.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33535:33"/>
            <p>The Streets of the <hi>Hague</hi> are very broad and clean, Houſes large, and ſpruce without, and very neat within, even to a nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is often troubleſome; which chiefly ariſes from the Pride of being thought to be, and admir'd for a good Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife: This Place is populous, abounding with Gentry and rich Citizens, many of which keep Coaches; in a word, the <hi>Hague</hi> is really a very pleaſant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Place.</p>
            <p>Here are a great many Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, ſome of all ſorts of fine Flowers, Fruits, Herbs, and Roots, in great Quantity; all which are generally larger than ours, except Colliflowers, and Artichokes, in which we really excel them; and tho' our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cherries, red and white <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33535:34"/>Curran's are not ſo large and beautiful as theirs, yet they are much pleaſanter in their taſte, ſweeter, to be eat without Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and theirs not; they have abundance of black Curran's (which we have not, here and there only in a noble Man's Garden that is curious) they have an unpleaſant, Phyſical taſte, and therefore they put them into Brandy, as we do black Cherries, and, they ſay, 'tis a great Cordial.</p>
            <p>Their Fiſh-Markets is well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and abounds with live and dead, but moſt of the firſt, for even the common People will hardly purchaſe the laſt; here is great ſtore of Salmon, which they ſlice alive, for then it ſhrivels up, which they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem the beſt; tho' we did not <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33535:34"/>agree with them, for we choſe a great intire Piece, and had it boil'd, and with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sawce brought up to the Table: Perch, Soals, and Flounders in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, which they fell by the Pound, four Pence, five Pence, ſix Pence, ſeven Pence, and eight Pence, which is a high Price, and rarely happens, but after very hard and long Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and a ſucceeding cold Spring, and wet Summer, which deſtroys the Spawn, and hinders the growth and increaſe of Fiſh in general. Here are alſo Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of Cheeſe, Butter, Baskets, Stockings, Silk, Thred, Lace, and a great many Baubles.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Fleſh-Market here to be paſt by, for there is choice of all ſorts of Butchers Meat, and very good in the Kinds;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33535:35"/>their Veal is altogether as white, and rathe larger than ours; the Mutton ſhort and tender, (ſeeding much upon Turneps) is ſweet, but not ſo much in eſteem (nor indeed ſo good) as our <hi>Banſted</hi> and <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Mutton; their Beef good, but ſmall and thin, brought from <hi>Denmark,</hi> and not very fat, not ſtalled as ours; in that they fall ſhort of us; for 'tis agreed by all Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, that the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> is the beſt Beef in the World, far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding all, even the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who have good Land, and breed good Cattel; but the difference appears in the ſalting more than the ſight, for no Beef endures that like ours, and that for the longeſt Voiages; however, to this Market at the <hi>Hague</hi> is the beſt in all theſe Provinces <pb n="61" facs="tcp:33535:35"/>brought, becauſe 'twill yield the beſt Price here. Theſe People are very neat and cleanly about their Fleſh, Butter, Cheeſe, and other Things; nay, the meaneſt among 'em have not only good but clean Linnen. Here are two Butter-Markets, one Wholeſale, t'other Retail, a great deal in each; the <hi>Dutch</hi> are not call'd <hi>Butter-Boxes</hi> in jeſt, for they eat abundance, and carry it in Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Boxes, and keep it in ſuch on board their Ships, which might give occaſion to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> to call them ſo; in return of which, they nick-name the Engliſh <hi>Starts;</hi> that is, <hi>Tails;</hi> tho', as we told them, they had little reaſon, for we us'd to ſee theirs oftner than they ours, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving oftner beat them in Sea-Engagements than they us.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33535:36"/>
            <p>To divert our ſelves we went to ſee their Spin-Houſes, or
<hi>Bridewell,</hi> where old Women are confin'd for Drunkenneſs, and young ones for Whoredom; here's not an idle Body in this Place, ſome Spinning, others ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Lace, others Plain-work; they come to the Barrs and hold out a Plate to beg our Charity, and there entertain us with ſome Liquoriſh Diſcourſe. They are kept here for Weeks, Months, and Years; all according to the greatneſs, or ſmalneſs of their Crimes. 'Tis alſo a Priſon for Debtors, which are not expos'd to view. Here we were told a pleaſant Story, the Fact thus; A young Gentleman of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> coming by Water hither in one of their common Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage-Boats, drawn by Horſes,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33535:36"/>was extremely Amorous upon a young Lady that was among the Company, and was ſo Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate in his Addreſſes, that he was very troubleſome, which oblig'd that Lady to give him ſome hopes of obtaining his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire when they came aſhoar, which made him quiet and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; as ſoon as ever they landed, he attack'd her afreſh by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſhe told him, that ſhe had buſineſs to do for her Mother, which would employ two or three Hours of her time, but that ſhe would meet him exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at Four at ſuch a Houſe, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him the Maſter's Name, (which he took care not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get) ſo they parted, he about his, ſhe about her Affairs; ſhe goes directly to this Place, and tells the Maſter that her Brother
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33535:37"/>would be there by and by and ask for her, that he was a very Debauchee, and ſo very lew'd, and extravagant, that her Father could not tell what to do with him, but ſent her to deſire him to receive him into his Care, and give him the Diſcipline of the Houſe, (this was a private
<hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> or Houſe of Correction,) which he thought might reduce him. The amorous Youth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at the limited Minute, and asking for ſuch a Lady, he was admitted, but preſently confin'd to a Chamber, and (according to the laudable Cuſtom) diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, and told that was all the Sport he muſt expect here; they kept him a Fortnight or three Weeks, and cool'd him, and ſo let him out.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:33535:37"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Hague</hi> is a very good Alms-Houſe, given by a private Gentleman; 'tis a handſom well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built Square, pretty Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Gardens to each, with all manner of Conveniencies; here are Threeſcore Women, half <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> half <hi>Papiſts:</hi> The reaſon of this mixture is, The Founder, who was of the <hi>Reform'd Religion,</hi> died before they were finiſh'd, and left the Perfecting of the Work, and Management of the Revenues, to a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> who put in half of his own
<hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old Buildings here are all of Brick; of which they have three ſorts, whitiſh, paliſh red, and deep red, better workt up and burnt than ours. Their new Buildings are of Stone, and Stone and Brick; magnificent,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33535:38"/>noble, and great, lofty Cielings, large Windows, very good
<hi>French</hi> Glaſs, but they have not Saſhes yet, being not ſo great Apes of Imitation as their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the <hi>French</hi> and
<hi>Engliſh.</hi> One would think Marble grew here; that is, that there were great and vaſt Quarries of it in this Country, for rich and poor, old and new Houſes, have all their firſt Floors pav'd with black and white Marble; not courſe and ordinary, but very good of the Kind, with great Variety in the manner of laying it: Nay, tho' <hi>Italy,</hi> whence it comes, be nearer
<hi>France,</hi> yet the preſent <hi>French</hi> King bought moſt of his Marble, for the fam'd Building at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> at
<hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Much Guilding, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; the firſt, upon Leather,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:33535:38"/>with which they hang many of their Rooms, both above and below Stairs, and cover Chairs; and alſo guild their Window-Shutters: Their Carving is in Stone at the Front of their Houſes. And ſo much for the
<hi>Hague,</hi> where we ſtaid a great while, and where we could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever be tyr'd or cloy'd with abiding.</p>
            <p>I have been the more Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in giving an Account of this Place, and of every Thing that is remarkable in it, becauſe 'tis ſo very much talked of by all Travellers in general. I had like to have omitted a Houſe (belonging to the Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> built by Prince <hi>Frederick, Henry,</hi> King <hi>William</hi>'s Grand-Father,) call'd <hi>Ryſwick,</hi> not far from the <hi>Hague,</hi> which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33535:39"/>we were ſo curious to take a view of; 'tis a very good Piece of Building, all Front, with a ſpatious Court before it, the Cie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling richly Guilt, and the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-Pieces, except two or three, which are Marble, with Pillars of the ſame; Floors of black and white Marble; good Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, but neglected.</p>
            <p>And now having reſolv'd to take our leave of the <hi>Hague,</hi> we went on board the <hi>Trecht Schuyt,</hi> or Paſſage-Boat, which is very large, and will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain between thirty and forty People, cover'd with a Tarpau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin, (a Piece of Canvas dipt in Tar, or Oil,) which in wet Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther keeps out the Rain, and in hot the Sun; which is to be thrown up, to let in the Air when they pleaſe; a ſingle Horſe <pb n="69" facs="tcp:33535:39"/>draws this Veſſel, rid by a Boy, who has a long ſlender Rope faſten'd to his Geers, and runs, or rather trots along upon the Dykes or Banks, three Miles, or a League an Hour conſtantly, ſtays for no Body, but puts off every Hour, juſt as the Clock has done ſtriking; the Fare is very reaſonable; this way of Travelling from Town to Town is very convenient, and tends mightily to the advancement of Commerce, and diſpatch of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, or Viſits. When you are upon theſe Canals on which theſe Boats float, you caſt your Eyes from the Water as from a Precipiece down to the Land, for ſo much higher is the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in theſe Countries than the Land, which chiefly conſiſts of Marſhes, full of Mills, of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <pb n="70" facs="tcp:33535:40"/>ſorts, the moſt that we ever ſaw flying in our lives; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is pleaſant: The
<hi>Dutch</hi> are great Improvers of Land, and Planters of Trees, of Ornament as well as Profit.</p>
            <p>In our Way to <hi>Leyden</hi> we paſt <hi>Voorbroock,</hi> and
<hi>Woorſconack,</hi> two ſmall Villages; and ſeveral Country-Houſes, belonging to Gentlemen, or rich Citizens, made pleaſant with Rows of Trees, and fine Walks before them.</p>
            <p>About ſeven in the Afternoon we came to <hi>LEYDEN,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leyden.</note> about nine Miles from the <hi>Hague,</hi> 'tis a very fair, large and rich City, in the Province of <hi>Holland;</hi> it ſtands on the River <hi>Rhine,</hi> (which divides it into thirty one Iſlands, join'd by one hundred and forty five Bridges, whereof one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33535:40"/>and four are of Stone,) and loſes it ſelf in the Sand, where endeavours have been, to no purpoſe, us'd to make a Sea-Port; 'tis but ſeven Miles from <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and twenty one from <hi>Amſterdam; Leyden</hi> is ſaid, by ſome, to be the Eye, by others, the Garden of
<hi>Holland,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the cleanneſs of its Streets, and the beauty of its Buildings; 'tis celebrated for its Antiquity, for its fine Impreſſions, and fam'd Univerſity, which was founded <hi>Anno</hi> 1575, adorn'd with a very good Library, a Phyſick-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, abounding with great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of choice and excellent Simples, brought with great care, and much trouble, from Foreign Parts, very remore: Here is alſo an Anatomical Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, which contains a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <pb n="72" facs="tcp:33535:41"/>Rarities, the Gifts of ſeveral Princes, and eminent Men; the Particulars of which are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The Head of an <hi>Elephant;</hi> the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Sopii.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of an <hi>Elk;</hi> the Gift of Dr. <hi>Job Paludarii.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin and Horn of the Head of a
<hi>Rhinoceros.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin and Horns of a <hi>White-Heart.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Crocodile,</hi> the four Feet of an
<hi>Elephant;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Juſtus Heurnius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Some <hi>Indian</hi> Darts.</item>
                  <item>A Trumpet made of the Rinds of Trees in
<hi>Moſcovy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Bow.</item>
                  <item>The Skin of an Animal inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Brazil,</hi> call'd
<hi>Tamandua Popo;</hi> the Gift of Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33535:41"/>
                  <item>The Snout of an unknown Fiſh from <hi>Brazil;</hi> the Gift of Dr. <hi>George Piſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Pair of <hi>Polonian</hi> Boots.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Leopard</hi>'s Skin.</item>
                  <item>A Pair of <hi>Laplander</hi>'s Breeches.</item>
                  <item>The briſtly Skin of a <hi>Brazilian</hi> Beaſt; the Gift of Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of a <hi>Piger;</hi> a very ſlow Animal, mention'd by <hi>Pliny.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Horn of an <hi>Ondland</hi> Ox.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Muſcovian</hi> Monk's Hood.</item>
                  <item>A Cithern, which the <hi>Coſſack</hi>'s, lightly arm'd, make uſe of.</item>
                  <item>A Pair of <hi>Moſcovian</hi> Breeches, and a Coat.</item>
                  <item>A Pair of Stilts or Skates, with which the <hi>Norwegians, Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> and <hi>Frieſlanders</hi> run down high ſnowy Mountains, with almoſt an incredible ſwitneſs; the Gift of <hi>Arnold Williams.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33535:42"/>
                  <item>The Head of an <hi>Elephant;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Adrian Pauwe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Dog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Heron,</hi> a Bird whoſe Dung burns what it touches.</item>
                  <item>A Leathern Boot, brought from the <hi>Streights,</hi> of St. <hi>David</hi>'s.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Bird, call'd a <hi>Shoveler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Bone of the hinder part of a large old <hi>Whale;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Adrian Pauwe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Bone of a <hi>Whale</hi>'s Snout.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a young <hi>Whale,</hi> taken out of the old One's belly.</item>
                  <item>The Hide of a Sea-Horſe.</item>
                  <item>The Skin of an <hi>Alce,</hi> a wild Beaſt like a Deer.</item>
                  <item>The Teeth of a <hi>Whale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Snout of a Fiſh, having Teeth in the form of a Saw, and is therefore call'd a <hi>Saw-Fiſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:33535:42"/>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Bear.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Cow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Wolf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Baboon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of an <hi>Aſs;</hi> upon which ſits a Woman that kill'd her Daughter.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of an <hi>Ape.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Cat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Buck Goat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Woman</hi> of ſeventeen Years of Age, who murder'd her Son.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a large <hi>Bear.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Hog;</hi> the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Hart.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Horſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a large <hi>Piger;</hi> the Gift of
<hi>Piſo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Lepor Marinus,</hi> a Fiſh inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the muddieſt part of the Sea, and caſteth Snot out of his Mouth.</item>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:33535:43"/>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Sheep-ſtealer</hi> of
<hi>Haerlem,</hi> hang'd.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Pirat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Ferret.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Sheep;</hi> the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a gelded <hi>Buck Goat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Woman,</hi> call'd
<hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Hamburg,</hi> ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled for Theft.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of an <hi>Ape.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> (ſitting upon an
<hi>Ox</hi>) executed for ſtealing of Cattle; the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Greyhound.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Dog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> that hang'd himſelf.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of an <hi>Otter,</hi> and of a large
<hi>Greyhound.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Covering of a great <hi>Mumie,</hi> 
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:33535:43"/>upon which is engraven the Effigies of <hi>Ceres.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A young <hi>Elephant</hi>'s Head.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Ferret;</hi> an unknown <hi>Sea-Fiſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Sea <hi>Hedge-Hog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of a <hi>Wild Boar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Lapwing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Beaſt call'd <hi>Tatou;</hi> the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Squirrel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of a <hi>Sea-Calf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Snout of a large <hi>Saw-Fiſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Whale</hi>'s Yard.</item>
                  <item>The Skin of a <hi>Man</hi> tann'd.</item>
                  <item>The Entrails of a <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Eaſt-Indian Tyger;</hi> the Gift of Prince
<hi>Carpenter,</hi> Governor in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> a Surgeon.</item>
                  <item>The Effigies of a <hi>Pruſſian</hi> Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, who ſwallow'd a Knife of ten Inches in length, which was cut out of his Stomach, and he liv'd eight Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33535:44"/>the Gift of <hi>Dan. Becker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Piger;</hi> the Gift of Prince
<hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Two Bones grown to the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Norway</hi> Houſe, built of Balcks, or Beams, without Mortar, Brick, or Stone.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of an <hi>Eagle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Beard of a young <hi>Whale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Panther.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Snout of a Fiſh call'd <hi>Piſcis Serratus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Chair of a Root of a <hi>Tree</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally grown ſo, from <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Peter de Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of a <hi>Ray,</hi> or <hi>Skate,</hi> from
<hi>Angola,</hi> a Kingdom of <hi>Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sceleton</hi> of a <hi>Badger.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Bladder of a <hi>Man</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33535:44"/>four ſtoop, (which is ſomething above two
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Gallons) of Water.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Formica Vorans,</hi> or <hi>Piſmire</hi> Eater; the Gift of Pr. <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Crocodile;</hi> the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Entrails of a Man, of which is made a ſhirt; the Gift of Mr. <hi>John Leeuven.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Sea Dog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Some <hi>Tyger's Skins;</hi> the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of a Man dreſs'd as Parchment.</item>
                  <item>A Surgeon's Inſtrument, call'd <hi>Gloſſo Comion;</hi> that is, an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in which broken Pieces are ſet, and bound up.</item>
                  <item>A large <hi>Indian Crab.</hi> A <hi>Sea Calf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Civet Cat;</hi> the Gift of Dr. <hi>Theod. Gool.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of an <hi>Eaſt-Indian Dog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33535:45"/>
                  <item>A Sea <hi>Starling.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The skin of a large <hi>Serpent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The skin of a Woman.</item>
                  <item>The Inteſtines and ſtomach of a Man.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Tyger</hi> from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Beaſt call'd <hi>Tatou.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A huge <hi>Serpent,</hi> upon which hang a <hi>Man</hi>'s and a <hi>Hog</hi>'s ſtomach; the Gift of Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Warlike Arms us'd in <hi>China.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Whale</hi>'s Operator.</item>
                  <item>A great Faulchion, or hooked Sword of the
<hi>Chineſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Certain human Bones grown to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</item>
                  <item>The Head of a <hi>Sword-Fiſh,</hi> a known Enemy to the
<hi>Whale;</hi> the Gift of Dr. <hi>Sam. Bloemaert.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Coney.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Sea <hi>Hedge-Hog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Fiſh, call'd <hi>Orbis Piſcis,</hi> which is
<hi>Libra Can.</hi> with a great <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33535:45"/>Belly of a Cheſnut-colour, and is unſavoury Meat.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a large <hi>Coney.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of a wild <hi>Boar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Swan.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Cock.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Pigeon.</item>
                  <item>A Shield made of a large Sea Tortoiſe-ſhell; the Gift of <hi>John ab Ilpendam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A kind of <hi>Baboon,</hi> call'd by the <hi>Dutch</hi> a
<hi>Boſh Manneken.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Four or five <hi>Chineſe</hi> Songs; the Gift of <hi>P. de Carpentier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Two Horſes Hides of the ſame Nation.</item>
                  <item>The Bone of a Whale's Tail.</item>
                  <item>A ſtrange Sea-Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>The Skin of a Child, when firſt born.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Bear;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Daniel Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:33535:46"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galcus Levis,</hi> a hurtful ſort of Fiſh, we call it a <hi>Hound-Fiſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of a huge Serpent.</item>
                  <item>The Inteſtines and Stomach of a large Man.</item>
                  <item>A City of <hi>China,</hi> printed by the ſame Nation; the Gift of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter de Carpentier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Man on Horſe-back; the Gift of Dr.
<hi>de Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of a Sea-Horſe.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>French</hi> Noble-Man, who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd his Siſter, and alſo mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd her, was beheaded at <hi>Paris,</hi> and beſtow'd on the Anatomy by Dr. <hi>Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Bill of a ſtrange Bird.</item>
                  <item>The Mummy of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prince, above eighteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years old; the Gift of <hi>David de Willem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Beak of the Bird <hi>Rhinoceros,</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:33535:46"/>or <hi>Topau;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Adrian de Paevis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Sable.</item>
                  <item>Unbleach'd <hi>Egyptian</hi> Linnen.</item>
                  <item>The Head of a <hi>Rhinoceros.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Roll of white <hi>China</hi> Paper; the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Mic. Pauwe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Stone of a conſiderable big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, taken out of a Maids Kidney; the Gift of <hi>Don. Otto. Heurnius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Coral-Tree, taken out of the <hi>Eaſt-Indian</hi> Sea; the Gift of Dr. <hi>John de Laet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Six Stones taken out of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of an old Profeſſor, <hi>John Heurnius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Pot in which is <hi>China</hi> Beer.</item>
                  <item>Two <hi>Vertebrae</hi> out of the Neck of a
<hi>Rhinoceros.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A great Jaſper-Stone, or Blood-Stone from
<hi>Arabia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33535:47"/>
                  <item>A <hi>Roman</hi> Lamp which burns al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways under ground.</item>
                  <item>Some <hi>Roman</hi> Arms a thouſand Years old; the Gift of <hi>Dan. Giſius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Wings of a flying Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Crab-fiſh; the gift of Dr. <hi>Jo. Dam. Boſſu.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An Hand of a Mermaid; the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Toad-ſtool, above a hundred and ten Years old, which grew in the <hi>Haerlem Meer;</hi> the gift of <hi>Pet. Scriverius,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Foot of a Sea-Monſter; the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A <hi>Lizard</hi>'s Skin from <hi>Brazil;</hi> the gift of Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Gold-Ring from <hi>China;</hi> the gift of Dr. <hi>John Hoogkamer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of an <hi>Indian</hi> Squerril.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Mole.</item>
                  <item>The Claw of an <hi>Eaſt-Indian</hi> Crab-Fiſh.</item>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33535:47"/>
                  <item>A Glaſs containg the Subſtance with which they are wont to preſerve <hi>Mummies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All the Arteries of the Liver.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Tyger</hi>'s Head; the Gift of Prince
<hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Head of a Beaſt from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> call'd <hi>Barbirouſa,</hi> is half Hart, half Hog, and is bred in the Iſland <hi>Celebes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Petrefied Toad-ſtool.</item>
                  <item>The Head of a <hi>Sea-Hog</hi> from <hi>Brazil;</hi> the gift of <hi>W. Piſo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Hand and Foot of a <hi>Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> the gift of
<hi>Fred. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalinek.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A precious Stone in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> call'd
<hi>Heliotropium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Three Claws, with the Horn of a young
<hi>Rhinoceros.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bean.</item>
                  <item>A dried black Arm.</item>
                  <item>A Book printed with <hi>China</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33535:48"/>the gift of <hi>Francis Porſiin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Mouſe.</item>
                  <item>A Thunder-bolt; given by <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chier de Moucheron.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Arm of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hero.</item>
                  <item>An <hi>Egyptian</hi> Fly.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a new-born Child.</item>
                  <item>A Flying-Hart; given by <hi>Francis Schurmans.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Egyptian</hi> Urn, in which is an <hi>Abortus</hi> embalm'd, above a Thouſand Years old.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Viper,</hi> or <hi>Flying-Adder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Cheek-bone of a <hi>Mummy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Arteries of a Man's Liver.</item>
                  <item>A Sea-Spider from <hi>New-York;</hi> given by Dr.
<hi>Herman Bloen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Capricus Rondeletii.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Egytian</hi> Night-Owl.</item>
                  <item>The Blood of a <hi>Crocodile.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Bladder of a <hi>Dog.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33535:48"/>
                  <item>A Piece of Bread of new and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hnown Meal.</item>
                  <item>A Mallet, or Hammer, that the <hi>Savages</hi> in
<hi>New-York</hi> kill with; the gift of <hi>Herman Bloen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arm</hi> of an <hi>Egyptian Mummy;</hi> given by
<hi>David de Willem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A little Bone taken out of the Pizzel of a Wolf.</item>
                  <item>A little Stone found in Eagles Neſts, call'd <hi>Lapillus Aetites.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Stone taken out of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach of a Gooſe, brought from the <hi>Streights</hi> of <hi>Magellan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Bladder</hi> of a Man.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lapis Nephriticus,</hi> or the Gravel-Stone.</item>
                  <item>A Stone found in the Head of a Sea-Calf.</item>
                  <item>A <hi>Bone</hi> of the Hearing Organ of a Whale; the gift of Dr. <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cuculo,</hi> commonly call'd a Sea-Cock.</item>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:33535:49"/>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a <hi>Fitcher.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A ſmall Bone taken out of the <hi>Penis</hi> of a
<hi>Beaver.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The double <hi>Bladder</hi> of a Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Frog.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arteries</hi> of the Liver.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Hedge-Hog.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Drinking-Cup of the Scull of a <hi>Moor,</hi> kill'd in the beleagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Haerlem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Water-Rat.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> young Crocodile from <hi>Egypt;</hi> given by Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Shepherd's Pipe from the Iſland of
<hi>Maltha;</hi> given by Dr. <hi>John Van Horn.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Chaffinch.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> wooden Effigies of <hi>Oſiris,</hi> whom the
<hi>Egyptians</hi> worſhipp'd as a God, now almoſt conſum'd with
<hi>Age.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An Image of <hi>Iſis,</hi> giving ſuck to her Son
<hi>Orus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33535:49"/>
                  <item>An <hi>Egyptian</hi> Coffer, in which are
<hi>Aromatical</hi> Spices, for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Bodies for Mummies.</item>
                  <item>Three <hi>Egyptian</hi> Idols, made of Stone.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Drinking-Cup, made of a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſe-Shell.</item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Serpent's Eggs.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Mole.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arteries</hi> of the Lungs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Water-Serpent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> brazen Effigies of <hi>Oſiris,</hi> the
<hi>Egyptian</hi> God.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arm</hi> of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hero, embalm'd.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Bone embalm'd.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Fiſh call'd <hi>Schincus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> little <hi>Egyptian</hi> Coffer, upon which is engraven the Effigies of <hi>Iſis,</hi> and in which is the Heart of an
<hi>Egyptian</hi> Prince embalm'd; given by <hi>D. de Willem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:33535:50"/>
                  <item>The Hip-bone of a Giant; given by <hi>Sam. Muſſenbrook.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arteries</hi> of the Lungs of a Pig.</item>
                  <item>Two ſtrong Idols; given by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid de Willem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Cruſe wrought in polliſh'd Marble.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Triangular Fiſh; given by Mr.
<hi>Huſenbrook.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Mummy of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prince, above thirteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years old; given by Dr. <hi>Jo. Baptiſt. Bartoliti.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Pair of Sandals or Slippers from the Kingdom of
<hi>Siam</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Skin of an <hi>Indian</hi> Lizard.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Pair of <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Shooes.</item>
                  <item>The Skin of a <hi>Molucca</hi> Woman, above one hundred and fifty Years old; by <hi>Richard Snock.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Lion's Head.</item>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33535:50"/>
                  <item>Two Images of the <hi>Japaneſes;</hi> given by <hi>Adrian Pauwe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Cheeck-bone of a Dog-Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Flying Dragon.</item>
                  <item>An Urn, call'd <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rna Ferulis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana,</hi> wherein the
<hi>Romans</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the <hi>Aſhes</hi> of burnt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; the gift of Dr. <hi>Daniel Gyffus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Woman's <hi>Pudenda,</hi> with Hair of a great length.</item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Lamprey.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Roman</hi> Earthen Veſſel; given by Dr. <hi>Dan. Gyfius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> gilded Copper Idol from <hi>Siam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Roman</hi> Bean.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A China</hi> Pot; the Gift of Dr. <hi>Ja. Speck.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Box of white Powder, with which the
<hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> uſe to make the Hair fall off.</item>
                  <item>The Bough of a Tree fenced with Stone; given by Dr.
<hi>Harre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33535:51"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Pair of Shooes made of Man's Leather.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Pair of <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sandals; the Gift of Dr. <hi>Ja. Leuven.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Sea-Horſe out of the
<hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Some ſtrange <hi>Indian</hi> Fiſh, and a flying Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A Roman</hi> Lamp which burns eternally; given by Dr.
<hi>Dan. Ghiſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Sea-Spider.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> piece of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> grown in the ſhape of a Dog's Head.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Basket wherein are Crocadile's Eggs; the Gift of Pr. <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Lizard.</item>
                  <item>The Liver of a Man, in which is grown a Stone like a Ball.</item>
                  <item>The Rib of a Sheep, with three Branches ſprouting out.</item>
                  <item>The Hearing-Organ of a Man.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>China</hi> Figgs.</item>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33535:51"/>
                  <item>A Basket in which is <hi>Moſcovian</hi> and other Country Money.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Arteria Magna</hi> of a Man.</item>
                  <item>Some <hi>Egyptian</hi> Glaſſing, or Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Veſſels.</item>
                  <item>The Sceleton of a Serpent; the Gift of <hi>Adam Bornius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Diſh of <hi>Lapis Oſſifragus,</hi> or fine Bone-ſtone; the Gift of <hi>John Boumanno.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> Knife.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Stone which was found in the <hi>Os Sacrum,</hi> or the great Bone upon which the Ridge-bone reſteth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Ball call'd <hi>Manſa,</hi> found in a Cows Stomach.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> great <hi>Caſſia Fiſtula</hi> from
<hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil;</hi> given by Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> great deal of very large <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> the Gift of <hi>Daniel Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>An <hi>American</hi> Bean.</item>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33535:52"/>
                  <item>An <hi>Indian</hi> guilded Wooden Cup; the Gift of Dr.
<hi>Jam. Stelling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> black Fly, call'd a <hi>Beetle,</hi> brought from the <hi>Cape of good Hope.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Some grown Coral.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Cup made of a double Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan; given by Dr.
<hi>de Bills.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>Brain-pan</hi> of an <hi>Oſtrich.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Puff, or Muſhroom, of a vaſt greatneſs.</item>
                  <item>A Sceleton of a Child newly born.</item>
                  <item>A Sceleton of a Child, but four Months old in the Womb.</item>
                  <item>The Image of the Goddeſs <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune;</hi> the Gift of
<hi>D. Gyfius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> great <hi>Bone</hi> found in the <hi>Body</hi> of a Woman of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>larding,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ninety Years old.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> Sword-Fiſh.</item>
                  <item>All the Muſcles of a Man, very <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33535:52"/>curiouſly done, by Profeſſor <hi>Stulpent Vander Wiel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>All the Muſcles of a Child.</item>
                  <item>A young Hangman, married un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gallows.</item>
                  <item>Two new-born Children, very curiouſly anatomis'd.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Phyſick Garden is a ſquare but ſmall piece of ground, very well ſtock'd with almoſt all ſorts of Medicinal Herbs, Roots, Plants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; the choiceſt Things are kept in Glaſs-Caſes; on the left-hand is a Room full of Foreign Rarities, both of Sea and Land, very neatly kept.</p>
            <p>Then we ſaw the Printing-Preſs in the Univerſity Yard, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the fine Characters of Monſieur <hi>Jean Elſeviers;</hi> then the Univerſity, which is a neat <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33535:53"/>oldiſh Building; it has three Halls for Publick Lectures, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chambers, where they take their Degrees; upon the Table of one of 'em we ſaw <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Works, and ſome Civil Law-Books; the Profeſſor's Cloſets are full of extraordinrry Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. The Students have no Colleges or Halls to lodge and diet in, (as in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi>) but board in the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens Houſes; their Tutors are very careful of them, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in keeping them cloſe to their Exerciſes, both at Publick Lectures, and in their Private Examinations, for which they have appointed Hours, and at which they are very punctual: 'Tis a celebrated Accademy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving continually in it about two Thouſand, half Natives, and the <pb n="97" facs="tcp:33535:53"/>reſt
<hi>Hungarians, Grecians, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Polanders, French, Engliſh, Scots,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh;</hi> of which three laſt are computed about one hundred. Here they take their Degrees eaſier, and cheaper, and without that Pomp and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Expence in practice in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are but two Colleges, and thoſe very ſmall, not to be mention'd at the ſame time with the meaneſt in <hi>Oxford,</hi> or
<hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> nor are they endow'd, they receive their Maintenance from the Charity-Collections of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Miniſters; nor can any Students remain longer here than till they attain the Degree of <hi>Batchelors of Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a high very Tower, where they keep their
<hi>Aſtronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Inſtruments, and whence they <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33535:54"/>make their Obſervations, and Calculations of the Motions of the Celeſtial Bodies: This Place was built for the Uſe and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the
<hi>Aſtronomers</hi> an <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers;</hi> of the firſt they have ſome pretty Eminent, tho' of the latter none, that we could hear of, that Learning is not in much eſteem with them; tho' if it were divided into proper Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> into Mundane, or General Affairs of the World; Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or Particular Nativities, with their Revolutions, Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Profections, Tranſits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Horary Queſtions with their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions; and, laſtly, into the Weather, with its great variety and ſudden alterations: I ſay, if theſe four Parts, or Diviſions, were to be ſtudied, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by as many ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33535:54"/>with a College, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment, for that very Purpoſe ſet apart, it might prove of vaſt benefit and advantage to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, there being many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Things in Aſtrology, and very great Truths to be found out by a due application. But Prieſtcraft is every where ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, that 'tis oppos'd by thoſe Gentlemen, who think their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt would hereby be leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen'd.</p>
            <p>Here is an old Burgh, built by the <hi>Romans,</hi> or
<hi>Saxons,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Caſtle belonging to the Prince of
<hi>Liege,</hi> ſome Years ſince repair'd, and made a good Fortification, of great Uſe and Service againſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the renown'd Defence the City of <hi>Leyden</hi> made againſt them who beſieg'd it
<hi>Anno</hi> 1544, or <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33535:55"/>rather <hi>Anno</hi> 1573, preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Eaſter;</hi> which by a Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem was rais'd the third of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> following, by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who letting looſe the Waters, which were before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd by great Dykes, reliev'd the City, and ruin'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, who by this means ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd an entire Defeat; but now this Burgh is converted into a Garden, with a very pretty La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth in it, newly made up, and neatly kept: It belongs to a Tavern, and has drinking Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors in it; we went up by a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſteep aſcent of near a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Steps, whence we took a view of the Country round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have part of a Church here.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:33535:55"/>
            <p>Their <hi>Stadthouſe</hi> is a good old Building, and ſtands in a handſome broad Street.</p>
            <p>This City is very Populous, abounding with Strangers, led by Curioſity to ſee this Place, and its Rarities; as alſo by the reſidence of many to ſtudy, (as I ſaid before) having had the Fame of breeding up many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and learned Men in all Faculties.</p>
            <p>Here are alſo great Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Woollen, and Linnen-Cloth, Perpetuana's, Sayes, Serges, Stuffs, and Camlets; of the firſt they ſend abundance to <hi>Turkey,</hi> whence they bring Mohair to make their Camlets; alſo they import fine Wool from <hi>Spain,</hi> and courſe from
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Poland:</hi> Abundance of <hi>Walloons</hi> live here, as alſo of many other <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33535:56"/>Nations, concern'd in their Woollen and Linnen Trades.</p>
            <p>This City has under its Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ſeventy two Towns in the Country of <hi>Rhinelandt,</hi> and has very great Privileges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it appear'd very Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious againſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> upon all Occaſions. <hi>Anno</hi> 1616 it was burnt by Misfortune, but ſoon re-built, more ſtately than ever; 'tis a very pretty, neat, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Place, fine Houſes, large and clean Streets, many Canals, adorn'd with Rows of Trees on each ſide; ſituated upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the Centre of
<hi>Holland.</hi> Here are ſeveral great Libraries, as indeed there are in many Towns in this Province, ſeveral belonging to private Men. Here was
<hi>Heinſius</hi> the famous Poet born; and here lies buried the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33535:56"/>great <hi>Scaliger</hi> in our <hi>Lady</hi>'s Church, built <hi>Anno</hi> 1370, which now belongs to the <hi>French</hi> and
<hi>Walloons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Place are famous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the <hi>French, Italian,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongues, for Arms, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, Muſick, Mathematicks, in the Whole, or Parts, and Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. We went to St.
<hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, built <hi>Anno</hi> 1121, indeed their Churches are generally good ones: The Walks round this City are pleaſant, and the Fortifications very agreeable to behold. A Native of this Town, was the Taylor, who, to his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, made himſelf King of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in
<hi>Munſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence we went by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>HAERLEM,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haerlem.</note> twelve Miles farther, a large and fine City in this Province; 'tis ſeated near a <pb n="104" facs="tcp:33535:57"/>Lake of that Name, a League off the Sea, and four from <hi>Leyden,</hi> with which it has Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by a Canal made <hi>Anno</hi> 1656. There are near it delicate Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, a delightful Forreſt, and a great number of fair and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Villages, which make it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſant. Within it is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with fine Piazza's, a good (tho' old) Town-Houſe, (the worſt in all this Province) and many other Publick Edifices. Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Philip</hi> the Second King of <hi>Spain,</hi> made it a Biſhop's See, ſuffragan to the Archbiſhop of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht. Anno</hi>
1347 it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt reduced to Aſhes, but ſoon after re-built much more ſtately than ever. In the Year 1572 the Inhabitants ſhoke off the
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoke and Religion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33535:57"/>and embraced the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. They were beſieged not long after by <hi>Frederick To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi>'s Son, and after a ſtout and bloody reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for the ſpace of eight Months, were forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves at Diſcretion, whereby they became a Prey to the
<hi>Spaniard</hi>'s Cruelty; but this Town was ſince re-taken by the
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited States.</hi> This Place glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the Invention of Printing, ſaid to be found out here firſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 1420, by one <hi>Lawrence Coſter,</hi> one of the Burghers, whoſe Stock of Letters was ſtollen away by a Servant of his, and carried into <hi>Germany,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went himſelf, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd them at <hi>Cologn,</hi> and ſoon after perfected his Invention at that Place, having in <hi>Haerlem</hi> 
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:33535:58"/>only found out the way of printing on one ſide of the Paper; the firſt Book he ever printed is kept in the <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> for thoſe that are Curious to ſee it, and is <hi>Tully</hi>'s <hi>Offices. Germany</hi> would fain rob <hi>Haerlem</hi> of the Honour of this Uſeful Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and
<hi>Mayence,</hi> a conſiderable and ancient City in the Circle of the
<hi>Lower Rhine,</hi> puts in her Claim firſt: Printing was long before this in Uſe amongſt the <hi>Chineſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here they brew good Beer, which is ſent to <hi>Frieſland</hi> by Sea, which puts it into a new fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by that means makes it much better, and more pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; as our <hi>Hull</hi> Ale is when brought to
<hi>London</hi> by Shipping. 'Tis a neat, well-built, pleaſant Place, having Rows of Trees on <pb n="107" facs="tcp:33535:58"/>each ſide of their Burgh-wall, or Canal, of which they have not ſo many here as in other Cities: Their Gates are removed, and their City enlarg'd, for their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants encreaſe, and grow rich, being renowned for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the fineſt Linnen Cloth, Tiffanies, Damask, and flower'd Silks, Stuffs, Ribands, and Tapes; they have Mills by which they can weave forty or fifty Pieces at a time; they make the fineſt Thred and Tapes for Lace in the whole World; their Blea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries ſurpaſs all other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; their Water whitening Cloth better than any other in the
<hi>Seventeen Provinces;</hi> they uſe Butter-Milk frequently to make their Linnen look ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately; they are very Skilful and Curious in Waſhing, for <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33535:59"/>hither is ſent from <hi>Amſterdam, Leyden,</hi> and all round about, the fine Linnen, and choice Laces to be waſh'd, which the principal People of thoſe Places wear the whole Year about, but uſually have enough waſh'd in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to laſt them all the Winter, having by them always a great Stock of wearing Linnen. The <hi>French</hi> Court, ſome Years ſince, ſent for ſome of the chief Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, and were mightily pleas'd with their Skill and Neatneſs; rewarded them well, and ſent them back big bellied.</p>
            <p>Here they have a moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Grove, like a little Wood, divided into Walks, where on Sundays and Holy-days, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of
<hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and other Places, reſort to divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:33535:59"/>
            <p>Here is one of the faireſt and largeſt Churches in all theſe Provinces; in the Walls whereof remain to this day Cannon Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets ſticking, which were ſhot by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> during the Siege thereof, before-mention'd; in this Church are three Organs, two old, one new, all kept very neatly; as alſo the Models of the three Ships that ſail'd from
<hi>Haer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to <hi>Damiater,</hi> ſeizing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in which the Earl of <hi>Holland</hi> was kept Priſoner, and brought him away home. In the Tower of this Church hang two Silver Bells, which they alſo brought from thence, and now ring them every Night at Nine a Clock.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haerlem</hi> is the Second City of <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſends its Deputies unto all the Colleges of the Government.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33535:60"/>
            <p>After having ſeen all that was Rare and Curious, and diverted our ſelves as long as we thought fit, to which End we ſpar'd nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Money nor Time, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to leave this Place, and advance towards
<hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which we did, and ſo for ſix Stivers apiece we took the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage Boat, and when we were come half way, we ſtept out of that, to go into another, and then we ſaw a ſtately Houſe, where the Lords, call'd <hi>Dyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graves,</hi> meet, and ſit, to take Care of, and Repair the Sea and Land Dykes, or Banks; each has his Appartment provided for him. Here are two very large Sluces, having Gates to let Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in or out from the
<hi>Haerlem meer.</hi> Near this Place, about the Year 1672, a part of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank <pb n="111" facs="tcp:33535:60"/>was broken by a ſtrong North-Weſt Wind, overflowing all the Land betwixt <hi>Haerlem</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which coſt a vaſt and prodigious Summ to repair. They ſunk in this Breach four hundred ſmall Veſſels, fill'd with Earth and Stones, for a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to re-build the Wall upon, and by unſpeakable Induſtry, and immenſe Charges, at laſt compleated the Work. Here we met with a very pleaſant and remarkable Story, from an elderly <hi>Dutch</hi> Man, who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd us with it, till we almoſt got to our Journey's end for that Night. 'Twas thus; An eminent Farrier that liv'd near this Place, having an Apprentice that was ſo very dull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, that he could not, after ſome Years teaching, do any <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33535:61"/>manner of Thing relating to his Profeſſion; the Maſter being uneaſie, and unwilling to keep a Servant, that eat up his Bread, but did him no Service, one day brought him before the Burgo-Maſters, or chief Magiſtrates of <hi>Haerlem,</hi> and deſir'd that he might be diſcharged from him, urging that he was ſo great a Blockhead, that he could not make a Horſe-Shooe Nail, much leſs a Horſe-Shooe, or ſet it on either: The Magiſtrates ask'd the Fellow what he could ſay for himſelf againſt what his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter alledged; he replied, That he was above that Trade; upon which, his Maſter being ask'd by the Magiſtrates concerning the Youth's Birth and Parentage, declared, that he was a mere Scoundrel, and that he took him <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33535:61"/>in pure Charity, his Father and Mother were Labouring Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and but a little better than Beggars: Then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ask'd the Fellow what he meant; he anſwer'd, That he could drain <hi>Haerlem-meer</hi> eaſier than make a Horſe-Shooe; at which the Burgo-Maſters (think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it next to Impoſſible) laught; however, they diſcharg'd his Maſter, and took the Youngſter in private, and examin'd him cloſely, and finding he had a Mathematical Head, they told him, they would advance a good Summ of Money, and ſet him at work; which they did, and when he had compleated his Engines, he fixt them, and in a ſhort time recover'd a great deal of dry Land; the Fame of which brought great Numbers <pb n="114" facs="tcp:33535:62"/>of People of all Qualities, and Profeſſions, to ſee this mighty En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer; and being told the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the Story, they were ſurpris'd: The Money be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expended, the Operator attended the Magiſtrates, and gave them an Account of it, and told them, he could not go on, except they would advance him more Money; which they (being mere
<hi>Mamoniſts</hi>) refus'd to do; upon which he cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drew off the Work-men, and in the Night deſtroy'd the beſt Engine, (in which the great Secret lay, and which was made in Private by his Hand alone) and pull'd out ſome Pins out of others, and in a very ſhort ſpace of Time laid the whole Land under Water as it was before; away he fled to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> getting
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33535:62"/>far enough out of the reach of his Employers, who now (tho' too late) began to be ſenſible of their Stingineſs, and would have given double the Summ to have had their Engineer again; however, to obtain their End, having heard where he was (by a Letter he ſent to a Friend at
<hi>Haerlem,</hi>) they made freſh Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to him, and new Offers, which he ſlighted; then they made uſe of Stratagems and Slights to get him away private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and by force; which failing, they addreſs'd the Governor (a
<hi>Spaniard,</hi> then in open War againſt the <hi>States</hi>) to ſend him back; who, calling him before him, examin'd the Lad about the Affair, and finding how baſely the Magiſtrates had dealt with him, and what an ingenious <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33535:63"/>Fellow he was, refus'd to gratifie them; then they attempted by new, large, and more generous Offers, to gain him to come vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily to them; to which at laſt he conſented, and being upon his Journey to <hi>Haerlem,</hi> fell ſick of a Fever, and ſo died by the way, and with him died alſo that mighty and matchleſs Project; ſince which they have not been able to do any thing in that Matter, the Water of that
<hi>Meer</hi> being vaſt in its extent, and very deep, even to be Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable, for we ſaw ſeveral Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Burden then upon it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſail.</p>
            <p>About half an Hour paſt ſeven that Evening we arriv'd at
<hi>AMSTERDAM,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> a vaſt, rich, populous, and beautiful City, equal to moſt in Chriſtendom,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33535:63"/>the Metropolis of all the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> in North
<hi>Holland,</hi> in the Territory of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> once Imperial, now ſubject to the <hi>Sates-General</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited-Provinces:</hi> It ſtands on the River <hi>Amſtel,</hi> by an excellent Haven, (tho' the Coaſts of <hi>Holland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Sands, which render their Harbors more difficult and dangerous to enter,) nigh the <hi>Zuider-Zee,</hi> 80 Miles North of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> 210 almoſt Eaſt of <hi>London,</hi> 250 almoſt North of <hi>Paris,</hi> 380 South-Weſt of <hi>Copen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bagen,</hi> and 560 almoſt Weſt of <hi>Vienna.</hi> Longitude 24 <hi>deg.</hi> 00 <hi>min.</hi> Latitude 52 <hi>deg.</hi> 29 <hi>min.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This vaſt City was at firſt but a ſmall Caſtle, and call'd
<hi>Amſtel,</hi> taking its Name from the River upon which it was built, and gave Title to the <pb n="118" facs="tcp:33535:64"/>Lords the Founders. Soon after the Inhabitants encreas'd, and apply'd themſelves to Fiſhing, and were contented to live in thatched Cottages; this Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begat a Trade amongſt their Nighbours, and mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enrich'd themſelves; ſo that the Happineſs and Commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Situation invited a greater Number of People to come thither, to reſide there; which, from a ſmall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Village, ſoon made it a very conſiderable Town. <hi>Anno</hi>
1235 they had certain Immunities granted them by <hi>Florentius</hi> the Fourth; after this they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build 'em Bridges and Towers; the Inhabitants alſo built new Houſes in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, and then the Borough began to take upon it the Name <pb n="119" facs="tcp:33535:64"/>of the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which was then united to the Country of <hi>Holland,</hi> and having receiv'd new and greater Privileges, which were confirm'd by ſucceeding Princes, they by their Trade and Induſtry became very Potent; tho' as yet this City had no Walls but only a Paliſado until <hi>Anno</hi> 1482. It ſurrender'd to
<hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> after a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and obſtinate Siege. Thus in length of Time, is this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Place become the moſt celebrated <hi>Emporium</hi> of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, vying with the greateſt Cities in the World, in the great number of its Ships, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency it has of fitting them out; it now drives the greateſt part of the Commerce which was formerly carried on by thoſe ancient and renown'd Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <pb n="120" facs="tcp:33535:65"/>
               <hi>Antwerp, Sevil,</hi> and <hi>Lisbon:</hi>
'Tis the Second City in the World for Trade, and the Firſt, we are of Opinion, for Wealth. 'Tis not ſo large (by much) as <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> or
<hi>London,</hi> tho' it has ſwell'd prodigiouſly of late Years in Big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Beauty, and Magnitude; theſe noble Streets, call'd by them Grafts or Canals, diſtinguiſh'd by the Names of <hi>Carſars, Lords,</hi> and
<hi>Cingel,</hi> &amp;c. are wondrous fine; the Fronts great, and lofty; good
<hi>French</hi> Glaſs, tho' no Saſhes; the Rooms large, and ſtately; Pavements of fine Black and White Marble; good Painting, but not much extraordinary Carving; Silver'd and guilt Leather of great variety, much in Vogue to hang their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers with; every Thing and Place very neat and nicely kept, <pb n="121" facs="tcp:33535:65"/>(ſometimes even to exceſs) and pretty well contrived, tho' (we ſpeak without partiality) not ſo well as the new Houſes building in and about <hi>London.</hi> The late Wars with
<hi>England</hi> put a check to the Buildings in, and Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Place, but as ſoon as they were over, they went on, and even now, during this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent War, (the worſt they ever were engag'd in) they are building in ſeveral Places, at the ends of the great Streets; but then the Houſes are but ſmall, and ordinary, compar'd to thoſe above-mention'd, being only fit for the middling People, whereas the t'other are for the wealthieſt Merchants, and greateſt Men among them.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing we took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of in this mighty and vaſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:33535:66"/>City, that was remarkable, was the manner of their laying their Foundations, on which they build all their Houſes, both great and ſmall, private and publick, which is thus; Above fifty or ſixty luſty Fellows, with a pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Engine of Braſs or Iron, force into the Ground a great many Maſts, (which occaſions a Saying among them, <hi>That their City ſtands upon Maſts, and lives by Maſts,</hi> meaning their Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,) upon which they build; the Earth is Boggy, Muddy at top, and a pretty way, but San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy lower, and their Houſes are firm, and ſecure, and ſtand as long as any other, tho' reckon'd better founded. This we ſaw in our way to the
<hi>Stadthouſe</hi> or <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> which is ſo renown'd all over the World, and which <pb n="123" facs="tcp:33535:66"/>call'd for our Curioſity firſt, and with which we entertain'd and diverted our ſelves a great while, as we hope we ſhall do the <hi>Reader,</hi> who (if he never ſaw it) will paſſionately deſire to go thither for the ſake of this noble Pile, and many other great Rarities, and Curioſities, no where elſe to be found.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> or <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> is a moſt noble and magnificent Pile of Building, all after the modern <hi>Italian</hi> Architecture; 'tis the ſtatelieſt Piece we ever ſaw, 'tis the Wonder and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of all the World, the Pride of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and the Glory of the <hi>Seven Provinces:</hi> The Entrance is mean, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, under ſeven ſmall Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>azza's, or Arches, which won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defully abate its Beauty, which <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33535:67"/>we told the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and which they own'd, for there is nothing gives a great and noble Piece of Building more Advantage, than a large Portico, or Entrance, which makes the approach Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent; and a large Cupolo to diffuſe the Light; which laſt this has, tho' in many places
'tis too dark, which is a great defect in Architecture; 'tis all of Free-Stone of the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Order, beautified with Braſs-Statues, and Marble Carvings, done by the greateſt Maſters of the Age. it is 282 Feet wide, 232 Feet deep, and 116 Feet high, beſides the Cupolo 50 Feet high, which is a very handſom one, and a great Ornament; in it is a good ſett of Bells, which ring not out like ours, but are made to chime.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33535:67"/>
            <p>This Foundation is laid as thoſe I mention'd before, and accounted to ſtand on 13657 Piles of Maſts driven (after the manner I ſpoke of, <hi>Page</hi> 122.) into the Ground; the front is adorn'd with a fine Piece of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Marble, 82 Feet long, and 18 Feet high, repreſenting this City in the Perſon of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with <hi>Neptune,</hi> Lord high Admiral of the Seas, and two Salt-Water Goddeſſes, his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, laden with the Fruits of the Earth, all on the Right-hand, bringing them as Preſents to this mighty Lady: And on her Left are two
<hi>Naides,</hi> offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Lawrels and Palms; and before her two
<hi>Triton</hi>'s dance, and ſound their Horns. On the top ſtands a Statue of Braſs, repreſenting Peace; and on each <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33535:68"/>ſide one ſhewing <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> each Figure twelve Feet in length. And on the Back of this noble Pile is ſuch another Piece of Carving, repreſenting the Trade and Greatneſs of the City. In the Centre ſits a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with the Hat and Wings of <hi>Mercury,</hi> with the Maſts and Sails, and other Rigging of a Ship behind her, and all ſorts of Navigating Inſtruments around her; at her Feet lie the two Rivers of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>k</hi> and <hi>Amſtel,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Europe, Aſia, Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> preſenting her their Products. Here are three Braſen Statues, as large as thoſe in the Front before-mention'd; one is an <hi>Atlas,</hi> with a very large Copper Plate; on his right-hand
<hi>Temperance,</hi> and on his left <hi>Juſtice.</hi> On the four Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33535:68"/>of this Great Houſe ſtand four Brazen <hi>Eagles,</hi> but Guilt very neatly, ſupporting an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown.</p>
            <p>Upon our right-hand as we enter'd this ſtately Fabrick, is their Hall of Juſtice, finely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd with Carved Works in Marble, with
<hi>Solomon</hi> on the <hi>Judgment-Seat,</hi> deciding the Controverſie between the ſham and real Mother of the Child; and ſeveral other ſuch Phanſies, too many to be particular in: In this Place is the famous Bank of the World kept, ſupported more by Credit than Caſh, tho' they want not the laſt, yet are not Maſters of ſo much as they vapour, of Millions of Tuns of Gold, each Tun valu'd at ten thouſand Pounds Sterling, (as we were inform'd by one who <pb n="128" facs="tcp:33535:69"/>knew the Secret;) but thus much may be ſaid for it, That it is a mighty Eſtabliſhment, the Support as well as the Glory of their State; they write off more Money here in one Day than at the Banks of <hi>Venice, Genoa, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> or <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> all together in two, and have more real Coin and Bullion than thoſe Three. They are very jealous of the new eſtabliſh'd Bank in <hi>England,</hi> and oppoſe its Intereſts as much as they can, for it draws abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their Profits away from thence; they have viſibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd, ſince that was ſet up, the Great Intereſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Eight <hi>per Cent.</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> give, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd the Foreigners to ſend Commiſſions for Subſcriptions; and it being a Parliamentary Security, they eſteem it Sacred,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33535:69"/>Sound, and Secure; no People in the World pay ſuch a Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to that Auguſt Aſſembly as theſe, for they are in Pain when ever there is the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion in the Senate, upon whoſe Conduct, the Good of the Kingdom, and almoſt all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> eſpecially of the
<hi>Reform'd Religion,</hi> they know, ſo much depends.</p>
            <p>The States and Magiſtrates of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> are the Security for this Bank; the Integrity of the Commiſſioners and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, the Safety of the Money here depoſited, the Promptneſs of the Payment, the Goodneſs of the Species, the Eaſineſs of Transferring it, the Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the State, are the great Inducements of the People of all Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> as well <pb n="130" facs="tcp:33535:70"/>as their own, to lodge their Caſh here.</p>
            <p>In this Houſe is the City Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for Debtors and Criminals. Here is the City Guard kept, by the Citizens only, where the Keys of the greateſt Gates are locked up every Night.</p>
            <p>Up a pair of good Stairs, tho' not large, but darkiſh, is the Common-Hall for the Citizens to meet, 'tis 120 Feet long, 57 broad, and 98 high. Here is the famous Moſaique or Braſs inlaid Globes, both Celeſtial and Terreſtial, in the Floor, wherein may be found all the known World, and all the Zodiacal Signs, Conſtellations, and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in the Heavens; the fixt Stars are moſt curiouſly done, plain and very eaſie to be found; we often came hither in wet <pb n="131" facs="tcp:33535:70"/>Weather to divert our ſelves with running over theſe Globes, each 22 Feet Diameter; this is a noble Piece. At the End of this Hall the Judges ſit, in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Chamber, to try all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Cauſes. Here are abundance of other Offices, or Chambers, as the Council-Chamber, where the Common-Council meet to make Laws, elect Burgo-Maſters, or Lord-Mayors, Sheriffs, Judges, Deputies to ſerve in the great Aſſemblies at the <hi>Hague.</hi> Here are Treaſury-Chambers, Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Accompts, an Office for the Commiſſioners for Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, who meet not to deſtroy (as in <hi>England</hi>) but to preſerve the Eſtates of thoſe infortunate Men, who are commiſerated by their Laws, and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not ruin'd with their <pb n="132" facs="tcp:33535:71"/>Families for ever. Theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners compound for the Debtors, and oblige their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors to be ſatisfied with what can be done, and ſuffer them not to hurry them away to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to lie and rot, (as ſome <hi>Barbarians</hi> let their Debtors in other places,) but receive part of their Debts, and remain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented till the Man be able to pay the reſt, who has a part of his Eſtate left to begin the World again, that is, to go to Trade again, who often by his Induſtry, and good Fortune, gets a great Eſtate, and paies every Body to a Farthing. This is Conduct, this is Management, this is Prudence to be prais'd: But when will the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be ſo happy to imitate them in this? Truly, I fear, never. <pb n="133" facs="tcp:33535:71"/>There need be no <hi>Mint, White-Friers, Savoy,</hi> or other <hi>Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> if they were put in practice; there need not, I ſay, be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtarving in all the Holes and Corners of the Town, who are capable of employing their Time well, and getting of Money, and have as good Heads, and as able Bodies, and are as fit for all ſorts of Buſineſs, as any People in the World: The
<hi>Engliſh</hi> are more Mercurial than the <hi>Dutch,</hi> but their National Conſtitutions are not ſo adapted for the Good of each Individual.</p>
            <p>Here the chief Officers for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Hoſpitals meet, and manage all Affairs relating to them very prudently. Here are Chambers belonging to the Secretaries, and others, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and too long to deſcribe;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:33535:72"/>with a proper Motto or Devize over each; as particularly that over the Chamber of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of Bankrupts, is cut in Marble,
<hi>Fortune</hi> flying away with Wings, Money-Cheſts turn'd up-ſide down, Mice and Rats eating Bags, Pens, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Books.</p>
            <p>Here is a great Magizine of Arms kept for the City's Safety and Service, all neatly kept, and preſerv'd in Preſſes; they told us they could arm, in four Hours time, twenty thouſand Men compleatly for Action At the top of this great Houſe are eight great Ciſterns, always kept full of Water, to be ready on all Occaſions, with Pipes of Leather to communicate them to all Parts of this Building, if any Fire ſhould happen; and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:33535:72"/>the Chimneys we ſaw were all ſecur'd by Copper within, to prevent even the Sut taking fire; and theſe great Precautions are us'd, not only becauſe of the vaſt Treaſure, and Accompts lodged here, but becauſe their old <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> which was but an ordinary Piece to this, was by accident ſuddenly reduced to Aſhes.</p>
            <p>This is one of the moſt popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and beautiful Cities in the World; their Buildings are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, large, and magnificent; their Streets broad, (no croud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there for the Wall, as at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>) clean, (even to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Slippers in Winter,) and neatly paved with <hi>French</hi> Peble, in Sand, which drinks up, and laid high, which throws off the Water into their Canals, <pb n="136" facs="tcp:33535:73"/>which are very large, and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous here, cleans'd by the daily ebbing and flowing of the Tide, and deep enough to bear Lighters of Burden, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade their Ships, and bring up the Merchandiſe to their very Doors; between their Houſes are moſt pleaſant Rows of Trees, and Lamps between them, and very thick, (one to two Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,) which in Night give a delightful Proſpect, and burn late, to anſwer the Ends of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Converſation: Theſe, as well as the Trees, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd with great Care, and he's a hardy Fellow that dares break the Glaſs of one, or the Boughs of t'other, and is ſure of ſevere Puniſhment, which they never fail to admiſter; and, to terrifie the Youth, and the Mob, they <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33535:73"/>have in ſeveral Places ſet up on a Board painted neatly; <hi>The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner whipping ſome, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the Hands of others for thoſe Crimes;</hi> which, by this means, are rarely heard of.</p>
            <p>Here is neither Court, nor Univerſity, yet wonderfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with People, of moſt Nations; a great many Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers always, paſſing and re-paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; 'tis a mighty Thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair.</p>
            <p>We walk'd round the Walls of this City, which are ſtrong with Baſtions, of modern Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Earth, faced with Brick, built
<hi>Anno</hi> 1660, forty or fifty Whole and Half-Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non mounted on Carriages; the Points flank one another, with a very large deep Ditch or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal round three parts of it; the <pb n="138" facs="tcp:33535:74"/>fourth being ſecur'd by an Arm of the Sea, ſeven ſtrong beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Gates, and ſeveral Guard-Houſes, ſixteen hundred Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in conſtant pay, cloathed and maintain'd by the City, whoſe Livery they wear, which is Grey Cloth lined, and faced with Green; four hundred do Duty every Night. 'Tis rare to hear of any Diſorders com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted here in the Nitht-time, notwithſtanding the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and variety of Inhabitants and Strangers, and their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Fiddling, all Night long, and Gaming, which they do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much here; no Quarrels, no Heads broke, no Watch-Men ſcour'd, or Aſſailants knock'd down; no Swords drawn, no ſending to the <hi>Counter,</hi> to lodge there all Night; no breaking
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33535:74"/>of Windows, pulling down of Signs, and Barber's Poles, (man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Acts indeed!) no, not the leaſt Miſchief done (at leaſt ſeldom;) if Drunk, they reel quietly home, and haſten to Bed to ſleep it away; Robberies Nocturnal are rare, the Clapper-Men (as they call them) go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout every half Hour, and make a Noiſe with their Rattles, and tell the Time of the Night, and trouble no Body with a <hi>Whither go ye?</hi> or, a
<hi>Come before the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</hi> and be ask'd twenty ſilly impertinent Queſtions. Indeed the Houſes here are made very ſtrong, abundance of Iron-work for Ornament and Safety, Shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters within and without, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thick, and with ſtrong Bolts, all neatly painted, to the very Garrets, with Green, Red and <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33535:75"/>White, which look very pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>We went into the new great Church, built by the <hi>Reform'd;</hi> here is the <hi>biggeſt Organ</hi> we ever ſaw, and plaies ſo very fine, that you would almoſt ſwear there were human Voices; nor did we ever ſee ſuch a Pulpit in the World as there is in another great Church, built broad at the lower part, and ſo up like a Pyramid, all very curiouſly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; then the Braſs Skreen of mighty Bars, and <hi>de Rutter</hi>'s (their Renown'd Admirals) Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument, erected at the States Charge, which coſt two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds Sterling; never was the Life of ſo great a Man ſo tamely and weakly thrown away, for he was ſent to aſſiſt the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> 
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33535:75"/>who (upon the Revolt of the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi>) made themſelves Maſters of that noble Iſland; a little before the Engagement, in which he was ſlain, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman went on board his Ship, and welcom'd him into thoſe Parts, and told him the <hi>French</hi> Squadron of Men of War was very ſtrong, and that he was troubled to ſee his ſo weak, and wonder'd the <hi>States</hi> would ſo expoſe Him, his Life, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; to which he anſwer'd, That <hi>where e'er his Maſter thought fit to venture their Flag, he would venture his Life;</hi> which he did, and loſt it, to his Maſters ſhame, to ſend him at the Head of a poor Squadron, ill mann'd and provided, that had commanded their whole Navy.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:33535:76"/>
            <p>Here are but thirteen Churches in this vaſt City, but then they are very large ones, much big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than ours in <hi>England,</hi> but no where ſo numerous; theſe all belong to the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> or <hi>Reform'd Dutch Presbyterians;</hi> ſome of which we were in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with, and found them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honeſt, moderate, good Men, not ſo hot and fiery as our own; they laugh'd at us for being ſo very zealous for, and ſpeaking ſo high of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> but we told them they had no reaſon, for we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood they were as zealous for the Church of <hi>Holland,</hi> and would ſuffer none but the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that to come into the Civil Government, which was a good way to preſerve it; which they own'd: And we added,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33535:76"/>that if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were as wiſe in that very Particular, they would be a happy Nation; but, as the Intereſts and Factions ſway'd at Court, ſo were the Church-men either valu'd or ſlighted, taken into, or thrown out of Place, and that this ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and changing of Perſons, and fluctuating of Councils, was very pernicious to the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Nation, and that the only means to keep the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſteddy, and unſhaken, was to fill all the Civil Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Truſt, Profit, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with ſound Members of the eſtabliſh'd Church of
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> who were the only Men that could and would ſupport Monarchy and Epiſcopacy, the beſt Church and Government in the World.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33535:77"/>
            <p>Here are two <hi>French</hi> Churches, one of 'em has been lately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged above a third part, 'tis well Wainſcoted, and has a ſmall plain Wainſcot Organ.</p>
            <p>Here is one <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, to which we went the firſt Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after our arrival, it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Popiſh Chapel; it has yet a Nunnery adjoyning to it, we ſaw ſome of the neat Nuns: Here is ſorry Preaching, a long, dull, tedious Sermon, an hour and three quarters, about two hundred Auditors, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times four or five hundred, all
<hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King of <hi>England</hi> has a Conſul here, who makes ſome ſmall Figure, and ſits in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Pew in the Church, and has ſome Reſpect paid him.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:33535:77"/>
            <p>Here is alſo one <hi>High-Dutch</hi> Church, or <hi>German;</hi> theſe are all allow'd the Uſe of Bells, and their Miniſters are paid by the Magiſtrates, as are their own, about 200 Pounds Sterling <hi>per Annum;</hi> ſome more, ſome leſs, beſides Preſents of Spices, and other Things, they receive once a Year, <hi>viz.</hi> at
<hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry numerous here, as alſo in the Towns and Villages in this and other Provinces; they have in this City alone fourſcore and five Chapels or Maſs-Rooms, have no Bells allow'd 'em, are oblig'd to have their Doors al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways open, and are tolerated, as all others are here; they have a large Square of Houſes for their Religious to live, but not to be cloiſter'd up in, who have a <pb n="146" facs="tcp:33535:78"/>Liberty to go, or ſtay at Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and to live ſingly, or to be married, which they like beſt.</p>
            <p>Great Numbers of <hi>Lutherans</hi> are here, and have a very fine Church; and <hi>Jews</hi> in abundance, who have many Streets here, and two Synagogues; one a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine one, and the largeſt in <hi>Europe</hi> (if not in the World) being much Superior to thoſe we our ſelves ſaw in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parts, where the <hi>Jews</hi> are moſt numerous; in the Yards they have large Schools to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Children, and inſtruct them in the Principles of their Religion, and to learn the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Language,</hi> as the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> is call'd.</p>
            <p>Here are <hi>Armenians, Browniſts,</hi> or <hi>Engliſh Independents, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> 
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33535:78"/>and <hi>Quakers,</hi> but not very many of the laſt: We were at all their Conventicles, and heard
'em mouth out their Noiſe and Nonſenſe, much againſt our Humour, but when we were once in, we thought 'twould be indecent to go out till all was over; they are very Zealous and Furious, and thunder out ſtrange ſort of rattling incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Stuff; we pittied their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, but found they retain the ſame Heat abroad as at home. All theſe Diſſenters from the eſtabliſh'd Church of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> muſt be firſt married by the Magiſtrates, and afterwards, if they will, among themſelves after their own Mode: But, as I ſaid before, they take care to exclude all theſe
<hi>Puritan</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders out of their Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33535:79"/>but they may go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Military, by Sea, or by Land, and be knock'd on the Head, if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Here are three great Sluces, and Bridges almoſt without number, which were formerly of Wood, but are now of good Stone, with very ſtrong, and neat Iron-work, not only of great Conveniency for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication betwixt Street and Street, but alſo of great Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Ornament. They are apt in Lazineſs (which is not commmon) to throw their Filth into their Burghals, or Canals, which cauſes ill Scents and Fumes, and which is a naſty thing, but
'tis prohibited, and puniſh'd when diſcover'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amſterdam</hi> is the World's Ware-Houſe, for here are vaſt <pb n="149" facs="tcp:33535:79"/>Magazines of all ſorts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe; hither are brought Goods from all Parts of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd Globe, and here they are laid up for a Market, and when ever they are in demand, hence they are ſent forth: Here is the great and general Store-Houſe for Corn, of which, tho' they have but little grows in their own Country, yet they ſerve their Neighbours with it, and are great Dealers, ſome of their Merchants trading only in this Commodity are ſaid to be worth above a hundred thouſand Pounds Sterling; they ſupply the Armies when in Campaign, and make great Advantage thereby, as alſo by the Exchange of Monies: Here are alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways vaſt Stores of Proviſions of War, for the Sea and Land <pb n="150" facs="tcp:33535:80"/>Service, Arms, Powder, Ball, Buff-Coats, Belts, Match, Ship-Timber, Iron-Works, Maſts, Pitch, Tar, Hemp, Canvas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then for Spices, with which they ſerve all <hi>Europe,</hi> and part of <hi>Aſia,</hi> which formerly was done by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> but now by the Dutch <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; ſurely 'tis not the Fate of Commonwealths only to be Maſters of ſuch mighty Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce!</p>
            <p>We hir'd a Yacht, and ſail'd up and down the River before the City, to view that and their Shipping, which lie before it in the Form of a Half-Moon, and look like a Wood; they have abundance of ſmall Veſſels con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſailing to and fro; we went to <hi>Sardam,</hi> a great Village
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:33535:80"/>about a League off, where we ſaw on the Stocks almoſt a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sail of Ships, all for the Merchants Service; they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work and under-ſell all their Neighbour-Nations, who us'd to come hither to buy Ships, which they could conſiderably cheaper than at home; they are very ſlight, ill-built Ships, like other things for ſale.</p>
            <p>Here are Mills of many ſorts, almoſt without number, chiefly to ſaw Timber for Ships; ſome to make Paper; the People are ſubtil and very rich, live ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Butter-Milk, Whey, with Herbs and pickled Herrings, and Rye-Bread; ſome great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants live here; others Inſurers, but moſt Ship-Builders and Ship-Carpenters: Their Houſes are very ordinary, and built of <pb n="152" facs="tcp:33535:81"/>Wood; two or three Churches, one ordinary, one new built of Brick; t'other lately enlarg'd, for the Inhabitants encreaſe. Here they build Ships of War upon occaſion, having abundance of Hands, and can run 'em up preſently: Here we ſaw ſome few Beggars, and except ſome Foreigners (moſt <hi>French</hi>) at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> we met with no Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars in all our Travels in theſe Provinces: The Natives chuſe to be Out-liers, rather than come to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where they ſhall have Bread, but they muſt work for it. In our return we took notice of the vaſt number of their Shipping, their <hi>Greenland</hi> Fleet makes a great ſhow, being about ſix or ſeven hundred Sail, which breeds abundance of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and employs abundance <pb n="153" facs="tcp:33535:81"/>of Shipping, but is not very gainful to the Adventurer, for they often make bad Voiages, killing but a few Whales; the very Ships ſtinks of their Oil, ſo we eaſily found them out. When we came aſhoar, we walk'd along their Keys or Wharfs, and view'd the Shipping that way, they were numerous indeed, that part of their Fleet which lies here conſiſts of about fifty Sail, great and ſmall, ſeveral new ones on the Stocks; they are now hard at work to get them ready, and to rig the reſt, to be early at Sea next Spring: The <hi>States</hi> have here a great Magazine for the Navy, and all things in great order, and well preſerv'd.</p>
            <p>We ſaw the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Magazine, conſiſting of Ware-Houſes, and Cellars, where <pb n="154" facs="tcp:33535:82"/>are vaſt Quantities of Spices of all ſorts, (the worſt and oldeſt of which they ſell firſt, and ſend to their Neighbours, Callico's, Silks,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis a large, new, well-built Houſe, with a Moat round about it, and Draw-Bridges; before it, on the River, is their Ship-Yard, a very large one, ſeveral new Ships on the Stocks, ſome of a thouſand Tuns, all their own; whereas the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company hire Ships for their Service: The <hi>Dutch</hi> Company is vaſtly rich here, and ſtrong in the
<hi>Indies,</hi> where, they ſay, they are not only Lords of Land of great extent, and of many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iſlands, but are able to bring to Sea in thoſe Parts a Fleet of forty good Ships of War; and on Land, an Army of as many <pb n="155" facs="tcp:33535:82"/>thouſand Men: They are really very great and formidable in thoſe Parts, having got all to themſelves; they have rook'd and worm'd out the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> (the ancient Diſcoverers of, and Traders to theſe Parts) and the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who have little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now to do in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and are like to have leſs, as they manage Matters. The Dutch <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company has a Sovereign Power and great Privileges granted them by the <hi>States-General,</hi> are very Politick in their Conduct, and Diligent in their Application, and aim not at the making themſelves and Families, but the Company Great; look to Futurity, and conſider the Conſequences of Things; they have tranſlated the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Teſtament</hi> in the <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33535:83"/>
               <hi>Indian</hi> Language, and pretend to be good Chriſtians, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to plant and cultivate the Goſpel among the <hi>Indians,</hi> (their conquer'd Vaſſals,) but prove themſelves very indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent (indeed not good Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts) in their Negotiations with the Engliſh
<hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and in their Treatiſes with the
<hi>Indian</hi> Princes, which they keep, or break, (French-King like,) (complain'd of, tho' co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied after) as ſuits moſt with their Intereſt and Advantage.</p>
            <p>They have a mighty Country in extent in <hi>India,</hi> and have built a great and beautiful City, and call'd it <hi>Batavia,</hi> have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified it like <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> At that Place reſides the General of the <hi>Indies,</hi> their chief Officer, who has Guards of Horſe and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33535:83"/>Foot, Court and State-Officers, Privy-Councellors,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Power to conclude Peace, or denounce War, and looks much like (tho' he be not) a Sovereign Prince. They are poſſeſt of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and other Parts of the Iſland of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> are conſiderable in the
<hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucca</hi> Iſlands, and thoſe of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Sumatra,</hi> and have Factories on the Coaſts of <hi>Bengal, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> and <hi>Cormandel,</hi> and in the Dominions of the <hi>Mogul,</hi> and <hi>Galcanda,</hi> have great Commerce in <hi>Perſia, China,</hi> and <hi>Japan,</hi> and have routed the King from the Iſland of <hi>Zeylan,</hi> and are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſters of that rich Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, while he, poor Gentleman, grazes it on the Mountains: Thus they uſually treat the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Princes, who firſt permit them to Trade with them <pb n="158" facs="tcp:33535:84"/>(which indeed is their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt) then they eſtabliſh Facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, build Forts, (which is weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done of thoſe Princes to let them,) and then bring Ships of War, and a good Army, and drive away the right Owners, and take Poſſeſſion for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, tho' they would be loth the <hi>moſt Chriſtian King</hi> ſhould ſerve them (not much better Chriſtians than his Majeſty) ſo here in
<hi>Europe,</hi> tho' he might and would have done it, if the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> had not ſtuck cloſe to them; for which ſurely they'll be very Civil to them in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> tho' I don't know when, yet I hope no more <hi>Amboyna</hi> Buſineſſes, which, I know, the
<hi>Dutch</hi> don't love to hear of; tho' 'tis an old Story, yet 'tis a very true one, and, I think, <pb n="159" facs="tcp:33535:84"/>one of the Crueleſt that was ever heard of.</p>
            <p>We took a view of both the Houſes belonging to the Dutch
<hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company in <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> one is the old, t'other the new Part of the City: Here they keep their General Courts of Sales, and Committees meet to diſpatch their Affairs; there are abundance of Chambers and Offices, in one are the Trophies which they have gain'd from the
<hi>Indian</hi> Princes whom they have vanquiſh'd. We were led into a Room, and gratified with the ſight of abundance of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber greece, Musk, Tea, and other rich Drugs; and into another where were great quantities of Cinamon, Mace, Cloves, and Nutmegs, brought from their Magazines, and making here fit
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33535:85"/>for Sale, by ſorting, as alſo min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them: Abundance of other Rooms and Appartments we ſaw, too many and too long to particularize. It ſhall ſuffice that we preſent you with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine and remarkable Story, told us juſt as we were taking leave, and ſtanding under the Gate. A Private Centinel that carried a Musket, and went hence in the Companies Service to <hi>Battavia,</hi> having ſignaliz'd himſelf by his Bravery in many Actions, was advanc'd to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Command in thoſe Parts, had Guards, a large Retinue, and liv'd wondrous Great, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd for a time, but in the ſpace of a few Years was reduced to extream Poverty, and became a very Sot; being uneaſie in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> he return'd to
<hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:33535:85"/>and having ſpun out ſome time, and could get no Employment, once more took a Musket on his Shoulder, and went away for <hi>Battavia</hi> to try his Fortune a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, (which ſeldom fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the Aged, but uſually is laviſh of her Graces to the Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and the Gay;) but what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of this Gentleman in this Second Adventure, we were not inform'd; but by this Story we took notice of the great Incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and Mutability of all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary Things.</p>
            <p>We were ſeveral times on the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Exchange, which is much crowded, and which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with Buſineſs, and great Merchants, (many of which, by great Loſſes, have gone off this War,) who correſpond to and with all Parts of the diſcover'd <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33535:86"/>World: This Building is oblong, of Brick and Stone, far ſhort in Beauty and Magnificence of the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> (tho' as capacious,) being an old Pile; has no Shops round about it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, as ours, nor about it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, only ſome few inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Toy-ſhops at one end above Stairs. The Merchants here take great freedom of talking of and cenſuring all the Actions of all the Sovereign Princes in the World, and obſerve no <hi>decorum</hi> in their Expreſſions, for which they are much to blame, as we told ſome of our Acquaintance, who thereupon furniſh'd us with an agreeable and remarkable Story of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant, who on this <hi>Exchange</hi> talk'd very freely of one of the leſſer (tho' Sovereign) Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> 
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:33535:86"/>and ſpeaking meanly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible of him, (his Envoy <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito</hi> being preſent, took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, ask'd his Name pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, and ſet it down in his Pocket-Book,) it hapned not long after, this very Negotiator had Buſineſs in that very Prince's Country, and being curious to ſee the Court, was met there by the Envoy who heard his foul Language againſt his Maſter on the <hi>Amſterdam-Exchange,</hi> and who knew him again, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his Name, found 'twas the ſame Man, and ask'd him if he remember'd ſuch Words; which he endeavour'd to evade, but the Time, Place and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany being told, he was mute; the Envoy told him 'twas now in his Power to ruin him, but he would not do it, but diſmiſs'd <pb n="164" facs="tcp:33535:87"/>him with this Advice; <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth Commonwealths Man</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>have a Care how you treat So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Princes, for the unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Freedom you take at home, might have coſt you your Life abroad.</hi> Nay, to our knowledge, upon that
<hi>Exchange,</hi> a ſawcy Raſcal (a Broker) had the Impudence to wiſh all the Princes in the World in their <hi>Raſphouſe,</hi> or
<hi>Bridewell;</hi> ſuch Liberty of Speech do theſe wanton Republicans take, and are fond of their Chains, <hi>viz.</hi> their heavy Taxes and Impoſitions, their Servitude being prodigious, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the name of Freedom. The ſame irreverent and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Diſcourſe they have in their Coffee-Houſes, which is for want of good Senſe and good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; for in all the Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="165" facs="tcp:33535:87"/>which we had (and which was a great deal, and with the principal Magiſtrates and States, and Top Traders, who are mere Merchants) both in Private and Publick Houſes, and in our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages from Place to Place, we met with very few refin'd Heads, (except amongſt the <hi>States,</hi> who are for the moſt part very prudent, ſober, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Men, of ſtanch Reputation and great Integrity, of good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and not rais'd from Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Herrings and Butter-Boxes, as reported by ſome untravell'd Sparks,) but two at <hi>Amſterdam, viz.</hi> a Poet and a Civilian, who were indeed very witty Men and extraordinary Company, we were often with them, they ſpoke <hi>French</hi> fluently, which is very common here, and, we think, <pb n="166" facs="tcp:33535:88"/>more univerſal than <hi>Latin.</hi> Milk-Coffee with Nutmeg, and Coffee with Liquoriſh infus'd, are much drank by the <hi>Dutch</hi> in thoſe Houſes.</p>
            <p>The Government of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd City is excellent, the Magiſtrates wholly attend their Office, and look carefully after the due execution of their Laws, which are the Life and Soul of the Commonwealth: The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which is here general, would be an inſupportable Grievance, and cauſe daily Complaints, but that it is fairly eſtabliſh'd, and faithfully collected. Here is a Senate of thirty ſix States men, who continue in that Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment during life, by a Privilege the Citizens have quitted, who in former Times elected them annually; but when their City <pb n="167" facs="tcp:33535:88"/>grew vaſt, the number of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors encreas'd and often fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Tumult; which to prevent they have eſtabliſh'd that great Council, who fill up their own Vacancies themſelves, and chuſe the Burgo-Maſters, and Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins, (Lord-Mayors and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) who are the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; of the firſt there are four, one preſides, and ſerves two Years, the other three are annually elected: Theſe great Officers repreſent the Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the City, and diſpoſe of all the Offices in the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, keep the Bank, and the Keys of that and the City Gates, make all Iſſues and Payments, have the whole Power, and are the ſole Judges of what is for the Honour, Safety, and Intereſt of this Body Politick; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33535:89"/>and entertain Foreign Princes and Ambaſſadors, and perform all the Publick Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>There are nine Eſchevins; of which ſeven are annually elected, the Senate chuſes fourteen, and the Stadtholder (King <hi>William</hi>) approves of and confirms ſeven. They are Judges in all Cauſes Civil and Criminal, and are Men of great Integrity, of a clear and unſpotted Reputation; their Penſions are ſmall, and their Port, Equipage and Retinue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; they think it a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Honour (as well as their Duty) to ſerve their Country: The Burgo-Maſters and Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins have it in their Power to make their Families, by getting their Sons, Nephews and Friends into Honourable and Profitable <pb n="169" facs="tcp:33535:89"/>Employments. The Schout is a great Officer, like our Sheriff, ſeizes Criminals, and ſecures them, and preſerves the Peace of the City. The Penſioner is like our Recorder, being Learn'd in the Civil Law, who informs the Senate, Burgo-Maſters, and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chevins what are the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Country, and makes all the Publich Speeches. Treaſurers and Under-Officers there are in great number, too tedious to mention. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the ſeveral Cities of the
<hi>Seven Provinces</hi> is (in a manner) the ſame.</p>
            <p>Then we went to Viſit their Alms-Houſes, which are nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and well fill'd, giving Lodging and Diet to above twenty thouſand Poor: Thus much may be ſaid, in pure ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <pb n="170" facs="tcp:33535:90"/>That the
<hi>Dutch</hi> Charity is very great and extenſive, they are very liberal, they give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, tho' it be but a little at a time; their Collections in their Churches are frequent, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly manag'd to prevent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, ſo gathering the Alms, that one knows not what the t'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gives; the Velvet Purſe or Bag which is handed about be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deep and not wide; and to put them in mind to prepare their Coin, a little Bell is fixt to the Stick, to which the Purſe is faſten'd, and which they ſend from one to another, through every Pew; Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants always give ſomething. Theſe Charity-Houſes are ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, noble, large, and well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd; we prais'd their Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Conveniences, and told <pb n="171" facs="tcp:33535:90"/>them, it was our Opinion, Houſes of that kind ſhould be rather Commodious (as theirs) than Magnificent, which was fitteſt for the Palaces of Princes, and not the Hoſpitals of the Poor. They have made Proviſion for the old Men and Women toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeparately and for Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows by themſelves, then for Children of both Sexes, who are numerous, and neatly dreſs'd, in party-colour'd Cloth, their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Garment half red, half ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colour; more eſpecial Care is taken of Citizens Children; tho' Foundlings, or the Iſſue of Strangers, are not excluded this Benefit of their Charity.</p>
            <p>We ſaw their <hi>Bedlam,</hi> a very neat old Building, tho' far ſhort of that in <hi>Moorfields,</hi> but rich in Stock, and indeed not ſo
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33535:91"/>full of mad Folks, as the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here they have a Fool-Houſe, no where elſe to be found in the World, not but that there may be as many of that ſort of tame Creatures in other Countries; and this may be ſaid, That how many ſoever there are without, there are very few within theſe Doors: 'Tis a ſmall old Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where there is good Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Diet provided for theſe unhappy People; amongſt them there was a Woman that had the leaſt Head we ever ſaw, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much leſs than the natural Proportion.</p>
            <p>Hence we went to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital for Boies and Girls, whoſe Fathers were Members of the Eſtabliſh'd or National Church: 'tis a good well-built ſquare <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33535:91"/>Piece, where the Children (while little) are kept cloſe to School, then put out Apprentices to Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicraft-Trades: Here is an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, and Shoe-makers Shop, wholly for the Service of this Houſe.</p>
            <p>Hence to the Spin-Houſe, the Priſon for Whores and Thieves, all were at work, ſome making Lace, others Plain-work, ſome Spinning, others mending Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen; ſome in for Weeks, others Months, and Years, according to their Demerits.</p>
            <p>Then to the Raſp-Houſe, which is a <hi>Bridewell,</hi> where are ſecur'd thoſe who have been near hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and have eſcap'd with burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between the Shoulders with three Croſſes, the Arms of
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam;</hi> ſometimes with a red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hot Sword on their Back, to
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33535:92"/>ſhew how narrowly they ſay'd their Heads, and to caution 'em to beware of the next Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; here, after a ſevere Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, they are doom'd to a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Impriſonment, from three to five, ſeven, nine, eleven, and thirty Years, ſome to perpetual; all to bodily Labour, to Raſp (which is to cut with a double-teeth'd Saw) fifty Pounds of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil (a hard Wood for the Dyers uſe) every Day, or be drubb'd luſtily with a Bulls Piſſel, and if that won't do, they are put into a Dungeon, and fed with Bread and Water; or elſe into a cloſe dark Vault, into which Water is let, which if they don't empty by pumping, will ſoon drown 'em, which ſoon brings 'em to work. The Profits of their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour are for their Maintenance, <pb n="175" facs="tcp:33535:92"/>and the Overplus to the Stock of the Houſe, or to be diſpos'd of by the <hi>States</hi> for the Publick Good.</p>
            <p>Here are alſo Houſes for Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, or wandering Beggars, common Gameſters, Sharpers, Sots and idle Folks, who are kept in this Place at hard work.</p>
            <p>Then to the Gaaſthouſe, where Entertainment is given (at the Publick Charge) to all needy Foreigners, of any Nation, four Days, and as many Nights; in which time they muſt find out their Friends, or get Work to maintain themſelves, or elſe they ſhall have Work provided for them by the Officers, which few like, but had rather chuſe their own.</p>
            <p>Upon the Juſtice-day (as they call the Execution here, which is
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33535:93"/>uſually Saturday) we ſaw a Man ſtrangled, which differs but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and that in the Word only, from Hanging; it is upon a Scaffold fix'd againſt the Stadt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; the Criminal is brought through
<hi>Solomon</hi>'s Hall, where his Sentence is read, as alſo on the Stage, then the Parſon prays with him, and he by himſelf, then mounts a little Cricket, and claps his Back to a Poſt ſet up on purpoſe, through which there's a Hole, into which the latter is put, and ſo twiſted hard about his Neck, the Stool kick'd down, and the Hangman all the while holding his Noſe, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his Breath, the ſooner to put him out of Pain.</p>
            <p>Another was beheaded with a broad Sword, which the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner keeps under his Cloak till <pb n="177" facs="tcp:33535:93"/>the Criminal is ready on his Knees, and the Cap over his Eyes, then off goes the Cloak, the Headſman approaches, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to pull the Cap a little more over his Eyes, in half a Minute whips off his Head, and very cleaverly. <hi>Haerlem</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes
<hi>Amſterdam</hi> with the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner; which tho' the biggeſt and richeſt City in all the <hi>Seven</hi> (as well as this) <hi>Provinces,</hi> yet has not the Privilege to have a Hangman of her own. He is a ſpruce Fellow, and goes well in Habit, and has Servants to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, and is uſually by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a Surgeon, and Bone-ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as well as Bone-Cutter, has a good Sallary from the Towns where he ſerves, and lives com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, tho' very few are found of his Company, it being thought
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:33535:94"/>the worſt in the World, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he has a Parſon with him.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time was a luſty ſturdy Fellow whipt for ſome leſſer Roguery, or Cheating, which was done while the t'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fellow was hanging; and after this manner, he was brought on the Scaffold with his Crime on his Breaſt in Capital Letters, and led about, then ſtript to the Waiſt, his Hands tied, and drawn up tight with a Cord to a Poſt, then the Hangman took up a good handful of large Birch (like that of Oſtlers Brooms) from a great Bundle which lay cloſe by, and ſlaſh'd him as faſt as he could, backwards and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, then took up a freſh hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſo on for ſix or ſeven Minutes; at which time the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33535:94"/>(who look on out of the <hi>Stadthouſe</hi> Windows) nodded to him to give over. Vaſt was the number of Spectators, (as always is both there and every where elſe at ſuch unpleaſant Sights) beyond what we ever ſaw, and moſt Mob; or <hi>Jean Hagel,</hi> as they call 'em; or
<hi>John Hail,</hi> or <hi>Canalia,</hi> or Canals, Sinks of Filth,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are alſo proper Houſes to receive, detain, and chaſtiſe Extravagants, Deboſhees, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, wicked, and lewd Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; of which having ſpoken pretty largely in the Account of the
<hi>Hague,</hi> we ſhall ſay no more here, but refer our Reader thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for full Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>All theſe Charity Houſes, as alſo thoſe of Correction and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, are neat and ſpruce, <pb n="180" facs="tcp:33535:95"/>furniſh'd with Pictures (which are ſo common in this Country, that Butchers, Coblers, and the meaneſt People, have a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and of the ſort pretty good) and well ſet out.</p>
            <p>In ſome of theſe Alms-Houſes there are fourteen or fifteen hundred, in others eight or nine hundred, and in the reſt four or five hundred Boys and Girls: Here alſo may any Body, Man or Woman, Native or Stranger, have a handſome Maintenance for their Lives, in a Houſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided on purpoſe, call'd the <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe,</hi> paying only a ſmall Summ of Money at firſt. The Charity of this renown'd City is very great, even beyond Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and above Compariſon, they are continually giving to the Poor, hardly a Bargain made <pb n="181" facs="tcp:33535:95"/>here, but they come in for a Snack, the Gods Penny is theirs.</p>
            <p>We took a walk in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon out of the City-Gates, to obſerve the Situation and the Country round about. We ſaw Mills innumerable, all in motion, ſome Water, ſome Wind, ſome Thatch, ſome Wood, (few Brick) to grind Colours for the Pot-Houſes, Corn for this City, ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Timber, draining Marſh-Grounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here the Land lies low, and the Water high, dam'd up for the Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and conveniency of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. The Air is thick, foul, and unwholſom; we fortified our ſelves with a good Doſe of old Hock every Day we liv'd, as the better ſort of
<hi>Dutch</hi> do, and the common with a Cup of <hi>Nantz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:33535:96"/>
            <p>We arrived to the <hi>Dooly-Houſe,</hi> a noted Tavern, where many of the Train'd-Band Officers are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well drawn in good Paint, in a great drinking Rome, the Wine is generally good at their Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Houſes, but the beſt was at the <hi>Heer-Logiment,</hi> but then the Price is higher: This is a noble Houſe, fit to receive and lodge a Prince, as it often does the leſſer Potentates of <hi>Germany,</hi> who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently travel thither, eſpecially in their Minority, when they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail to make the Tour of theſe Provinces; which well me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit their Time and Expence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their Judgments, as well as gratifying their Curioſities: The Accounts and Deſcriptions of Places and Things, well made, being indeed very delightful to read, but much more to view; <pb n="183" facs="tcp:33535:96"/>the Eye being in matters of that kind, much to be prefer'd to the Ear: The mighty Figure this Republick has, and ſtill does make in the World, her Wealth, Power, and Reputation, both at home and abroad; her Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Armies, Formidable Navies, and Foreign Alliances, are all well worth ſeeing and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>'Tis very obſervable here, more Women are found in the Shops and Buſineſs in general than Men; they have the Conduct of the Purſe and Commerce, and manage it rarely well, they are Careful and Diligent, capable of Affairs, (beſides Domeſtick) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Education ſuitable, and a Genius wholly adapted to it. The Men take all the Pleaſure, they go to Coffee-Houſes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns <pb n="184" facs="tcp:33535:97"/>and Treats, walk or ride in Chaſes abroad, play much at Cards, ſit up Gaming and Fud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling greateſt part of Night; and all is well, the good Wife gets and the Husband ſpends the Money; but this Compenſation the Woman has for all her Toil and Care, That at her Death (if ſhe drops before her Husband) ſhe can give away half the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. The Women of theſe Parts are all for making their Daughters and Nieces, or Grand-Children great Fortunes; they let the Boys ſhift for themſelves, they ſay they can beſt do it.</p>
            <p>We met abundance of <hi>French</hi> in this Place, both Miniſters and others, (moſt of the <hi>Reform'd Religion</hi>) the
<hi>Dutch</hi> are very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous to them in their Alms for their Support; here are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <pb n="185" facs="tcp:33535:97"/>Thouſands, ten for one in <hi>England</hi> or
<hi>Ireland.</hi> This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark we made (not once but often,) when we or any others, occaſionally ſpoke againſt the <hi>French</hi> King, they ſeem'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, tho' he has ſo bitterly perſecuted them; and, as we were inform'd by thoſe who knew it well, they us'd to rejoyce at his former Succeſſes in <hi>Flanders, Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and <hi>Catalina,</hi> and ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Occaſions, <hi>Nôtre Grand Monarque eſt invincible,</hi> which Note now is chang'd; the <hi>Dutch</hi> were offended at their Vanity and Weakneſs, becauſe from them they receiv'd their Bread.</p>
            <p>We went to the Butter, Cheeſe, Poultry, and Dog-Market; the three firſt were well-ſtor'd, but the laſt (which is every
<hi>Monday</hi> Morning) had but about twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <pb n="186" facs="tcp:33535:98"/>Curs in it, and thoſe very ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but every Woman muſt have one, the ordinary as well as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and good round Prizes they, for theſe hairy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions.</p>
            <p>Thence to the Market for green and dried Herbs, Seeds of all ſorts, and Roots for Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries; another of very fine Flowers in Pots, in great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities. Here is a Rag-market, and another for Tobacco, Pipes, of which they have very fine ones, curiouſly glaz'd and wrought, and great variety of Sorts and Prizes, for Sea and Land, ſhort ones with large Bowls for the Skippers and Tarpaulins, who keep them on board their Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and ſell them to the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers. Markets of Baskets, Chairs, Tubs, and Pails, all very <pb n="187" facs="tcp:33535:98"/>pretty; Grain, Bisket, Cakes, Eggs,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Two large Fleſh-Markets or Halls, being in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Houſes, great ſtore of Fleſh in both, and very good, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently cheap, and would be very reaſonable but for the great and laſting Exciſe; the Butchers and their Wives are neatly dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and cleanlier than ours: Here is alſo a Sawcidge, Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and Tripe-Market; they ſell in their Cheeſemongers Shops <hi>Bologna</hi> Sawcidges, and dried Salmon, both which they dreſs well, boiling in part, then fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt, and eating it with Spinage, over which they ſcrape Nutmeg.</p>
            <p>We hired a Yacht again, and ſailed for ſeveral Hours up and down the River to divert our ſelves: Upon a ſmall Iſland o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veragainſt
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:33535:99"/>the City is their ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gallows, (the Scaffold I mention'd before being ſet up only at particular times,) all of Free-Stone, Triangular Pillars, with Iron croſs them, with carv'd Work (a Lion) at the top of each; they firſt hang or ſtrangle the Criminals on the foreſaid Scaffold erected cloſe to the <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> and thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to hang in Iron are brought hither. The Wheel, or Croſs is ſeldom us'd here, (tho' often in <hi>France.</hi>) The <hi>Scotch</hi> Man that many Years ago attempted to burn their Fleet of Men of War, is here laid upon a Wheel ſet upon a high Poſt. Alſo a <hi>French</hi> Man that kill'd a Whore, who being bid by the Parſon to pray for the City and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſaid,
<hi>The Devil take 'em <pb n="189" facs="tcp:33535:99"/>all;</hi> and one or two more hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chains, (as we in <hi>England</hi> call it.)</p>
            <p>We had the Curioſity to go to ſee the Navy or Admiralty Office, which is a well-built Houſe, with good large Rooms, well painted, and fitly accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the Buſineſs; they have a Court of Juſtice within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, from which is no Appeal; they hang or ſhoot their Sea-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or Men for Cowardize, or neglect of Duty, and reward them roundly if they burn, ſink, or take a Flag-Ship, or any Ship of War, great, or ſmall, or do any conſiderable Service; they give them ready Money and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions when diſabled; great Care is taken of their Sea-men, their Wages punctually and juſtly paid, and their Widows and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:33535:100"/>conſider'd, and themſelves largely provided for in Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this Houſe are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Trophies hung up, taken from the ſeveral Enemies of this State.</p>
            <p>We hir'd each a Chaiſe (which is a ſmall Chariot on two Wheels drawn by one Horſe, which runs very ſwift, the Roads being ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and generally good, can tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel ſixty Miles a day,) and each got a Companion, and went to <hi>NAERDEN,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naerden.</note> the Frontier of the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> about ten Miles from <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> in our way we paſt through <hi>Muy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> a ſmall City, which has no Vote among the <hi>States,</hi> becauſe neither they, nor <hi>Weſep,</hi> another ſmall City, nor <hi>Naerden</hi> ſent any Deputies to the <hi>Hague,</hi> when the Foundation of the Union was <pb n="191" facs="tcp:33535:100"/>laid. This Town of
<hi>Naerden</hi> was almoſt deſtroy'd by Fire in the Fourteenth Century, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of it drown'd by the Sea ſoon after; but <hi>Anno</hi>
1455 it was re-built by <hi>William</hi> the Third of <hi>Bavaia,</hi> then Earl of <hi>Holland.</hi> The Citizens of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> made themſelves Maſters of it in the Year 1481, by a pretty Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, putting their Soldiers in the Habit of Country Women; who entring the Place on the Market-Day, eaſily took it; but the Inhabitants ſoon recover'd it, and put them all to the Sword. <hi>Anno</hi> 1486 this Place was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Aſhes, and ſoon re-built; but it met with a ſeverer Fate (at leaſt in the Perſons of the Burghers) from <hi>Frederick de To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo,</hi> Duke
<hi>D'Alva,</hi> who came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it with a Body of an Army;
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:33535:101"/>upon which ſome of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens open'd their Gates to let him in; notwithſtanding which, he fell upon the Inhabitants and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly murder'd them.</p>
            <p>It is now a modern Regular Fortification, and made prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſtrong, capable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Gariſon of eight or ten thouſand Men; it was begun <hi>Anno</hi> 1677, and perfected ſince the beginning of this War; it coſt above three (or rather ſix) hundred thouſand Pounds Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Here are ſix Bulwarks, four Ravelins, two Half-Moons, two Gates, and double Ditches, deep, with ſtrong Counterſcarps.</p>
            <p>The Town is but ſmall and ordinary; but this is the Frontier and principal Security of the whole Province, which is not the richeſt only of the Seven, <pb n="193" facs="tcp:33535:101"/>but of the Seventeen. In the Year 1672 the
<hi>French</hi> with Eaſe and by Treachery took it; but the Prince of
<hi>Orange</hi> (now King of <hi>England</hi>) re-took it in eight Days time, there being then no Fortification, but what the <hi>French</hi> had thrown up while they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd it. The <hi>States</hi> depending upon their Armies in the Field, took the leſs Care of this Place, now they have made it very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable.</p>
            <p>Here is a ſmall Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture; good Beer brew'd, fine, and but little inferior to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in pleaſantneſs of taſte.</p>
            <p>We rid round about the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which is Downy, almoſt like
<hi>Epſom,</hi> the Air pretty wholſom, and pleaſant: We were at a Country-Houſe of the late Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <pb n="194" facs="tcp:33535:102"/>
               <hi>Trump</hi>'s, a pretty Box, fine Gardens, Walks, and Rows of Trees, with a good Moat about it. We paſt by another of his Houſes, which the <hi>French</hi> burnt in the former War, <hi>Anno</hi> 1673 or 1674, much bigger than t'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>In our return we paſt through <hi>Weſep,</hi> a ſmall and inconſiderable City, where they brew good Beer.</p>
            <p>The Weather being pleaſant we made another Sally from
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> and viſited <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven Miles off; we paſt by <hi>Overkirk,</hi> a ſmall Village, which gives Title to a Lord, a Favourite, and poſſeſs'd of the Revenues hereof. We went through
<hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow,</hi> another ſmall Village, four Miles further; near which Place are the Ruines of an old Caſtle. <pb n="195" facs="tcp:33535:102"/>Then we came to
<hi>Liona,</hi> a great Town, ſeven Miles off: Thence to <hi>New Sluice,</hi> where we din'd upon roaſted Eels, which is very good Victuals, and well dreſs'd here, and is always ready at ſet times for Travellers. A Mile and half further is <hi>Brutil,</hi> a ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, where young <hi>De Rutter</hi> has a Houſe. We paſt <hi>Maerſem</hi> and <hi>Soulandt,</hi> two ſmall Places; and about three in the Afternoon we arriv'd at
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> a great, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, but weak City, Capital of the Province of that Name, one of the Seven United, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Archbiſhoprick, in the Circle of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but now ſubject to the
<hi>States:</hi> It is ſeated on a Branch of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> in a very convenient and fruitful Place.</p>
            <pb n="196" facs="tcp:33535:103"/>
            <p>We walk'd about the Walls, which are pretty high, and of Brick, but weak, and out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, ſurrounded with a deep, and broad Ditch; we paſt one of the Gates, and were ferried over to ſee the <hi>Pall-Mall,</hi> which is kept very neatly, ſhaded with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Rows of Trees on each ſide, preſerv'd by the preſent <hi>French</hi> King's immediate Command, who was there with his Army <hi>An.</hi> 1673, when he took this City without any Reſiſtance. Here is an Univerſity (erected by the <hi>States, Anno</hi> 1636,) but not ſo full as that at <hi>Leyden;</hi> tho' this, in our Opinion, is a pleaſanter Place, having better Air, and a finer Country about it, for we almoſt phanſied our ſelves in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> this being like ſome of our old Cities: Here many of the <pb n="197" facs="tcp:33535:103"/>Nobility and Gentry live, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the pleaſantneſs of the Place, being as it were a Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the noiſe and hurry of Buſineſs and Buſtle, conſtant in great, trading, populous Places. The better ſort of People here affect the <hi>French</hi> Mode, and, in ſome meaſure, their way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; whereas the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in moſt other Parts, are fixt to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, as the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> never changing it.</p>
            <p>We had the Curioſity to turn over the Manuſcripts lately found out, and now depoſited in the Clerks Houſe, (adjoyning to the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Church) where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many very ancient Bibles, and other curious Books fairly written, flouriſh'd, and adorn'd with Golden Letters, we ſaw five Unicorn's Horns, (as they <pb n="198" facs="tcp:33535:104"/>call'd
'em,) three long and thick, two ſmall and ſlender, like thoſe we have elſewhere ſeen (ſaid to be ſuch too.) Here are two ſmall braſen Images, ſuppos'd to be Heathen Gods, and by them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> (in moſt decent manner) we went to the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, which is a good old Piece of Building; the Chancel is let for a Joyners Shop, ſo little do they value what was once conſecrated (becauſe after the <hi>Popiſh</hi> manner) to God; the Congregation was ſmall, between one and two hundred, zealous Parſon and People, no <hi>Engliſh Liturgy</hi> read here, all <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> we view'd the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church, it was once ſo, tho' not now;
'tis very capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, built Abby manner, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="199" facs="tcp:33535:104"/>the old Faſhion, half of it fell in ſome years ſince, is not repair'd, becauſe the People are poor; here is a very lofty old Steeple, which we aſcended, and whence we took a view of this good, great, old City, and of ſeveral Churches and old Buildings, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Monaſteries and Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. In the chief is <hi>Van Ghent</hi>'s Monument, not ſo ſplendid as elſewhere; he was <hi>De Rutter</hi>'s Vice-Admiral, and ſlain by the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> in the Naval Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Anno</hi> 1672; he was of a noble Family of the Province of <hi>Guelderland</hi> (which is contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to this,) and Colonel of a Marine Regiment, train'd up to the Sea Service, and ready at all times for that, as alſo the Land Service, and in a ſcarcity of Sea-men, of great Uſe to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <pb n="200" facs="tcp:33535:105"/>that Defect, being Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious.</p>
            <p>The Streets are broad and clean, and the <hi>Stadthouſe</hi> a ſmall neat old Building, with a fair Piazza, or Market-Place. They take great Liberty here on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days,</hi> playing at Tables, Dice, and other Games with <hi>Cowries</hi> (or Blackmoors Teeth, as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren call 'em) at the Coffee-Houſes and Taverns, and have Muſick in the Publick-Houſes; the ſame is indeed practis'd at the <hi>Hague</hi> and <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> tho' in other Places they are a little more ſtrict, particularly in
<hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but they live very looſly in the Provinces of
<hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> buy and ſell frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on this Day, and eſpecially Proviſions; which is the more reaſonable, becauſe of Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers <pb n="201" facs="tcp:33535:105"/>paſſing and re-paſſing, and they muſt not ſtarve on this, tho' the <hi>Lord's-Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Day we hir'd a Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon to carry us to
<hi>Soeſtdike,</hi> nine Miles from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht;</hi> 'tis oue of King
<hi>William</hi>'s Hunting-Houſes, formerly much frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, there being abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Game about it, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Pheaſant and Partridge; it is a very pretty Box, and lately (that is ſome Years ſince) built, excellent Painting of Game, of all kinds, on the Walls and Cie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; the Lodgings are ſmall, but neat; good Gardens, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly planted and made up; a Park of ſix <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles about, five hundred Head of Deer; a pretty Engine or Mill, about three hundred Yards from the Houſe, which conveys Water <pb n="202" facs="tcp:33535:106"/>through leaden Pipes under Ground to ſerve all the Offices in the Houſe; very fine Walks, and rows of Trees about it, which renders it indeed very pleaſant. Having ſufficiently diverted our ſelves here with the Pleaſures ſuitable to the Seaſon, we went back to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> whence the next day we took a Boat with Sails and croſt the Riyer <hi>Y</hi> to <hi>Buyck ſloot,</hi> a village about a League off, and went thence by Water in another Boat drawn with a Horſe, to <hi>Promerent,</hi> a ſmall old City, two Leagues further, which has a Vote amongſt the <hi>States,</hi> and is very rich in her Finances. Here we hir'd two Chaiſes for two Days, and gave two Rix-dollers for each; we paſt through the <hi>Beemſter,</hi> Land ſo call'd, which
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:33535:106"/>the Sea formerly broke into, but was ſoon mill'd out:
'Tis very fat Paſture, feeding yearly abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Cattel of ſeveral ſorts, which are brought from <hi>Frieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Norway, Denmark,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Places lean, and here fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd. Many Country Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have fine Country Houſes, all round about, adorn'd with pleaſant rows of Trees, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with Paintings. We din'd at <hi>Schermerhoorn</hi> (a ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage) on Fiſh, becauſe we could have nothing elſe, nor indeed can we in any of the ſmall Towns through which we tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd; but this amends they make us, they are very new, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe always alive; nay, the common People (love their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſo well) they'ell not buy any Fiſh if they but only languiſh, <pb n="204" facs="tcp:33535:107"/>much leſs be dead: At this Place we had a mind to have a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Butter melted thick for Sawce, after the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which with much entreaty, and many good words, (the only way to work upon thoſe rough, clowniſh People) we were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, and in part had, for it was thick enough indeed, almoſt like haſty Pudding, for they had put abundance of Flower in, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they can't (that is, they won't) melt but boil But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Oil; they ſay, 'tis then beſt, being thinneſt, and goes fartheſt; they are, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, generally choice Cooks, but then 'tis only for their own Country Folks.</p>
            <p>Five or ſix Miles from this Place lies <hi>ALKMAER,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alkmaer.</note> which is one of the neateſt, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt, <pb n="205" facs="tcp:33535:107"/>(tho') oldeſt Cities in all the
<hi>Low-Countries,</hi> being built in the Year 1550; 'tis very clean, and handſomly pav'd; we rid through part of it, without ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping longer than to take a Glaſs of old Hock, and away we went to <hi>Egmont</hi> aſide
<hi>Hoef,</hi> three Miles off, a ſweet little Village; there ſtands an old ruin'd Caſtle: Thence to <hi>Egmont</hi> by the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, about a Mile further, a ſmall Village of Fiſhermen, whoſe Wives and Children were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Nets for their Husbands Service, who were then at the Salt Water getting Bread for them; ſo nothing is idle here: Thence through another Village call'd by the ſame Name, a Mile diſtant, it lies along the Sand Downs; here's a pretty Church, two Steeples, and the Ruines of
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:33535:108"/>an old Fort or Caſtle; the Counts of <hi>Egmont</hi> (fam'd in Story) are Lords of the Lands and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues all round about; we diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our ſelves with driving to and fro, and viewing the main Sea, and then return'd, and ſupp'd, and lay that Night at <hi>Alkmaer,</hi> and the next Day took an exact and particular view of this flouriſhing City. It was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly burnt and plunder'd by the <hi>Frieſlanders,</hi> and
<hi>Guelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> but ſoon re built by the Inhabitants, and fortified after the manner of that Age, but better by <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, Prince of Orange, who commanded ſome new and ſtrong Works to be added to it, which prov'd of manifeſt Advantage to them in the Sige which the
<hi>Spaniards</hi> laid to it, <hi>Anno</hi> 1573, under the Duke
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:33535:108"/>
               <hi>D'Alva,</hi> after he had taken <hi>Haer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> but they were forced to riſe from before <hi>Alkmaer</hi> with Shame and Loſs. It is the Capital Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the North Parts of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and ſends Deputies to the <hi>Hague,</hi> and has a Seſſion in the Admiralty, and a Stock in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, and a great Manufactory in Linnen-Cloth; the Country round about is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fruitful, and yields abundance of good Corn, Butter, and Cheeſe; of which laſt they have here a very fine Market, and the greateſt variety of ſorts we ever ſaw, ſome made with Anni-Seeds, ſome of Commin-Seeds, other of Sheeps-Milk diſcolour'd with green, all very indifferently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; and (in our Opinion) the very beſt was far ſhort of our Chedder, or <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> we had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:33535:109"/>Parmeſan-Cheeſe about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Pence
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Money <hi>per</hi> Pound, which indeed is firm and well taſted, but not ſo mellow and delicious as ours, (at leaſt in our Thoughts, nor are we partial.)</p>
            <p>We view'd their great Church, which is of curious Architecture, and one of the fineſt in theſe <hi>Provinces;</hi> 'tis neatly Wainſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and well kept; has a very fine, large, well-painted Organ, which plaies every Day from ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till twelve, and makes excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Muſick. And we ſaw their <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> which is a neat old plain Building, and ſtands in a fine, broad, cleanly, and well-pav'd Street. Their Fiſh-Market is well ſtor'd with great plenty of Perch, Carp, Eeels, Popes, Bleaks very large, and Jacks, <pb n="209" facs="tcp:33535:109"/>(but a few) all alive, and very cheap.</p>
            <p>So having ſeen all that was Rare and Curious, we mounted, and return'd to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where we ſpent two or three Days in finiſhing our Obſervations, and in buying ſome Toies, and fine Things (of which they have abundance) to preſent our Friends at our Return, we left this renown'd City, and paſs'd through <hi>Haerlem</hi> and the <hi>Hague</hi> once more, and ſo to <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> where we ſtaid two or three Days more; and thence went by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Dort,</hi> a beautiful, ſtrong and rich City in this Province, fam'd for the Synod held here about Religious Matters, <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. to determine the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies between the
<hi>Gomariſts</hi> or <pb n="210" facs="tcp:33535:110"/>
               <hi>Contra-Remonſtrants,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants</hi> or <hi>Arminians,</hi> about
<hi>Predeſtination,</hi> which then made a mighty Noiſe in the World. It ſtands on an Iſland, at the Mouth of the River <hi>Maeſe,</hi> and between three others, <hi>viz. Merwe, Rhine,</hi> and <hi>Linghe,</hi> ten Miles South-Eaſt of <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> is the firſt that Votes in the
<hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland;</hi> 'tis well built, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neat; had once the ſole Right of Coinage, but now other Places in theſe Provinces have got the like Privilege; the Sea frequently breaks in upon it, but more formerly, and drown'd above ten thouſand Perſons, and laid twelve Villages under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and once ſeventy Villages and one hundred thouſand Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <pb n="211" facs="tcp:33535:110"/>
            <p>The Earls of <hi>Holland</hi> in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Times kept their Courts there; it was alſo formerly the Staple Town for Merchandiſes Exported, but has now only the Staple of Rheniſh Wines, with which they drive a great Trade, and brew abominably, mixing <hi>French</hi> White Wine, and other cheap, and ordinary, thin, lean, and hungry Wines with that noble Juice, that it has in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner loſt the very natural taſte, and is indeed poor inſipid ſtuff; however, we met with good old Hock here, becauſe we were willing to pay the higheſt Price. Formerly the <hi>Engliſh</hi> bought abundance of this ſorry Wine, but they are grown wiſer, they now buy but little; the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Ladies for the moſt part now <pb n="212" facs="tcp:33535:111"/>drinking Red Wines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as formerly they fanſied that brew'd
<hi>Dort</hi> Rheniſh Wine moſt; however, there is yet à pretty good Trade with <hi>England</hi> for thoſe Wines, which the Wine-Coopers put into rich Canary, which makes it pleaſanter, and to them the cheaper, ſo they get the more Money by brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
            <p>And here we embark'd for <hi>Zealand,</hi> being reſolv'd to make the Tour of that <hi>Province,</hi> more particularly for the ſake of thoſe two Renown'd Cities, <hi>Midle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> and <hi>Fluſhing:</hi> But before we leave the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> (where we yet are) it will be fit to recollect ſomething (and very material) which we omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and had like to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got. <pb n="213" facs="tcp:33535:111"/>Before we left
<hi>Amſterdam</hi> we went to their Theatre or Play-Houſe, which is but ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, the Stage Muſick, Actors and Actreſſes, in their Perſons, and Habits ſo, and indeed there was but one Thing well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonated, and that was admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly well done, and was this; An old Fellow, who often ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd on the Stage in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Habit of a Serving-Man, and who was well known by both, and alſo by his Voice, for he anſwer'd to many Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, was by ill Fate, or bad Conduct (call it which you pleaſe) led into a Capital Crime, and having forfeited his Life to the <hi>State;</hi> he was brought out to die, (a Gallows of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try form, with a ſmall Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:33535:112"/>almoſt Breaſt-high, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the dead Body when cut down, was ſet upon the Stage) and being told, that he ſhould have his Life, if he would mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the Three Women (no contemprible ones) preſent on the Stage, he view'd 'em well, and ſaid, he was oblig'd to them for their Love, and to the <hi>States</hi> for their Kindneſs; <hi>but Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age being</hi> (in his Opinion) <hi>worſe than Hanging, he would rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo that Sentence.</hi> He made a ſhort Prayer, went up the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and was turn'd off; the young Women all the while on the Stage, ſeeing what paſt, and finding themſelves neglected, were mov'd with Pity rather than Revenge, approached the hanging Man, and ſaid, Tho' <pb n="215" facs="tcp:33535:112"/>he was a ſowre, ill-natur'd Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and would not eaſe us, of what has been troubleſome to us many Years, (our Maiden-Heads,) yet we will put him out of Pain, as ſoon as we can; upon which they pluck'd his Legs hard, which dropt down, and his Hands and Arms which did ſo, as alſo did all the reſt of the Man, his very Head and all falling through the Rope; which in leſs than a Minute was all put together again without a touch, and he appear'd on the Stage, and ſpoke to us all; nor could any Body diſcover how this Thing was done, which was the Rarity. The Comedy was call'd, <hi>Criſpin the Phyſician,</hi> (which we always reckon'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Cobler, but any thing
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:33535:113"/>will make a Doctor there, their Prices are accordingly, for we have ſeen a top Doctor take from an eminent Merchant a Half-Crown Fee,) with a ſilly Farce, of <hi>Hatred and Envy,</hi> which pleas'd them better than the Play, (becauſe they knew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.) The Pit is about two Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>Engliſh</hi> Money; the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery ſixteen Pence; behind the Pit Six-pence; but there the Mob will ſtand, breaking in by force ſometimes.</p>
            <p>The Players are kept poor by the <hi>States,</hi> to whom they (and all the Rope-Dancers, Puppet-Players, Lotteries, and all other Shows and Games whatever) pay, (towards the Maintenance of indigent old People) a great part of their Profit; ſome ſaid, <pb n="217" facs="tcp:33535:113"/>theſe do pay Two thouſand Pound <hi>per Annum;</hi> then no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they are ſo indifferenly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed themſelves.</p>
            <p>We were carried to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty common Bawdy-Houſe, call'd
<hi>the Long-Cellar,</hi> (we bid 'em put <hi>Sodom</hi> to it) preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd half a Dozen of plump Punks, ready to be employ'd, deſirous to go into a Box by themſelves; but we did not like this Kitchen-ſtuff, ſo we call'd for a Pint of White Wine, and gave it them, (not drinking a Drop our ſelves; for the Wine, and other Liquors in thoſe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Houſes, is always (like their Women) good for nothing. We had a little Liquoriſh Chat; they knew us to be <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſaid they lik'd our Country-Men
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:33535:114"/>beſt of any in the World; but we paid ſix
<hi>Stivers</hi> for our Wine, and ſo took our Leaves of theſe Ladies.</p>
            <p>We were immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by a Friend to a Houſe of Pleaſure, ſomething like; the Sign is, the <hi>Hoff van Holland,</hi> or the Court of <hi>Holland,</hi> and there were, in a Front-Room below ſtairs, a Knot of a dozen Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be hir'd, but all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, ſome working, ſome playing at Cards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We call'd for ſome Ale, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought in Bottles, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like (tho' not ſo good as) our Cock-Ale; we paid ſix <hi>Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> (which is about a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more than an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,) and treated the Ladies, who were handſomer, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="219" facs="tcp:33535:114"/>dreſs'd than t'other; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we had nothing more to ſay to 'em, than a little merry Tattle, ſo we paid, and mov'd off: Theſe Women attend the Service of the Publick, and, when agreed with, will go where you pleaſe, and do with you what you pleaſe. Theſe Things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niv'd at by the Magiſtrates, who ſay, 'tis unavoidably neceſſary, to prevent worſe Things, Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Rapes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Strangers, Travellers, and Mariners, long abſent from Women. They have many of theſe Houſes (as we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd) between forty and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they generally go under the Name and Shadow of
<hi>Muſick-Houſes,</hi> but we were content with ſeeing but two, taking
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:33535:115"/>their Words for the reſt; nor did we hear any Muſick there. This <hi>State</hi> makes an Advantage of theſe light Ladies, for each for her Admiſſion muſt pay three Pence; by laying out of which ſhe hopes to get more.</p>
            <p>In Summer the principal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion here is, to keep (as ſome) or to hire (as moſt do) a Chaiſe, and take their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes (often) or Wives (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) abroad into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and give them the Air, and a handſome Treat, returning home for the moſt part in the Evening. We have ſeen three or fourſcore of theſe Chaiſes, or ſmall Chariots abroad at one time, and together, tho' almoſt all of different Company.</p>
            <pb n="221" facs="tcp:33535:115"/>
            <p>In Winter the Ladies or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort of Women are, when the Froſt is hard, and the Streets ſlippery with hardned Snow, (which is often) taken abroad by their Gallants (often) or Husbands, (ſeldom except when firſt married) in <hi>Poliſh</hi> Sleads or Sledges, richly Guilt and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, cover'd with Embroidery of Gold, or Silver, or rich Silk, or Tapeſtry, drawn by a fine Horſe, richly Harneſs'd, with which they are very ſwiftly dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from Street to Street, from one Burgal to another, for about two Hours, and then brought home; whence after a little Reſt, and a diſh of Tea, they are attended to the Play-Houſe, and ſo home, and to Tea (not cold) again, and then to Cards, <pb n="222" facs="tcp:33535:116"/>which they uſe much, and hold long, both before and after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which they rarely fail of loving their Bellies as well as any People in the World, tho' they would be thought to do the contrary.</p>
            <p>The ordinary ſort of People divert themſelves but little in the Summer, except in Walking, (chiefly out of the City in <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>'s Afternoon,) and in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Skating, which they do very much, and promiſcuouſly, Boys and Girls, young Men and Maidens, and ſome few of the better Sort are ſometimes ſeen on the Ice at that Sport.</p>
            <p>The Merchandiſe in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, even the heavieſt,
<hi>viz.</hi> huge Fats of Rheniſh Wine, is drawn on Sledges, very low, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting <pb n="223" facs="tcp:33535:116"/>of two Pieces of Wood in length about ten ot twelve Feet, held together by two Pieces acroſs, and cover'd with Iron at top; and on this they lay the Goods, having no great hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy lumbring Carrs, like ours; the Brewers alſo carry their Drink abroad thus; all having a little Tub of Water upon the Sledge, which they often ſpill on the Ground, to make it go the glibber: The Drivers of theſe, as alſo of their travelling Waggons, are (like our Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Coach-men) often rude, and affront Folks; but then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Complaint to the Burgo-Maſters, they ſhall be puniſh'd by Suſpenſion, or otherwiſe, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeverely.</p>
            <pb n="224" facs="tcp:33535:117"/>
            <p>They have no Coaches like our Hackneys, that ply in the Streets, but you may hire a Sledge, which is the Body of a Coach upon a Sledge without Wheels, and drawn by a Horſe, the Coach is a handſom one, and the Horſe a good one, and the Fellow in very good Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit; and thus the better Sort are carried to Church, and to the Play-Houſe, and to Viſits; the Price reaſonable: But then at the <hi>Hague, Amſterdam,</hi> and other Places, you may hire (as we did often) a handſome Coach on Wheels, and a Pair of good Horſes, to carry you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where out of Town.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> every where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a great Decency in their Funerals, all the Men follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="225" facs="tcp:33535:117"/>the Corpſe (two by two, in handſome black Cloaks,) which are brought to the Church (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a forfeit of twenty-five <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> the firſt, and fifty the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond half Hour, to be given to the Poor) at two, or thereabouts, the Doors being lock'd up at three. The dead Body muſt lie three Days in open view, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Relations that it was a natural Death; and in ſome Places (in theſe <hi>Provinces</hi>) when any Body dies, there is a Truſs, or Bundle of Straw laid at the Door, where it continues till the Day of the Burial, and is great or ſmall according to the Age, and Sex, there being a very large Bundle for a Man, leſs for a Woman, and much leſs for a Child.</p>
            <pb n="226" facs="tcp:33535:118"/>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> are the worſt Nurſes in the World, they can't make a little good common Broth, Gruel, or Caudle, are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted too, and careleſs of the Sick; if you can recover by ſtrength of Nature, and a ſmall help from your Doctor, ſo; if not, you may die, they are very indifferent in the matter.</p>
            <p>In the Publick Houſes we pay for Pipes, Candles, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing; the Exciſe is very high, and heavy, ſo that it can't be avoided; but then you are ſerv'd with very fine Pipes (which you may break if you pleaſe) and large, white, tall Candles, made of pure Tallow, but bad Wick, and ſo don't burn extraordinarily.</p>
            <pb n="227" facs="tcp:33535:118"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Amſterdam</hi> is in no fear of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign or External Force, they can, when they pleaſe, cut their Dykes, their Banks, and lay the Country under Water, and ſo prevent the Enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>And now for the Province of <hi>ZEALAD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zealand.</note> to which we are under ſail, and very near; land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about eight in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Middleburg,</hi> the Capital Town in the Iſland of <hi>Walche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren;</hi> it was formerly a very ſorry Village, but now a noble, well-built, rich, and very ſtrong City; 'tis but twenty five Miles North-Eaſt of <hi>Bruges</hi> in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> it has a very great Trade in Times of Peace, eſpecially with <hi>France</hi> for Wines, (chiefly White, of which here is the <pb n="228" facs="tcp:33535:119"/>Staple) but now fits out almoſt a hundred Sail of Privaties, (by them call'd <hi>Capers</hi>) which extreamly annoy the <hi>French</hi> Coaſt-Trade, having done them more Harm than all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies beſides; they have ſome of forty and thirty Guns, which are ſent into the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and where they meet with rich Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, having abundance of <hi>French</hi> Ships (ſome of their Cargo's very valuable, eſpecially thoſe from <hi>Martinico</hi>) in their Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, taken this War: While we were there, they brought in ſeveral good Prizes.</p>
            <p>This Town has a good ſhare in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company's Stock, and have a Chamber here, and Sales of Goods that come from thence; the Merchants <pb n="229" facs="tcp:33535:119"/>coming from other
<hi>Provinces</hi> to buy them. Here were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome conſiderable
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, but now none, there being but little Trade between them and us: There is an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Church, about an hundred Auditors, all <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> from
<hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Parents.</p>
            <p>Here is an Exchange, and but an indifferent one, and thin of Merchants. The Churches here are large, and handſomly built, the Houſes alſo, but not ſo new and modiſh as at <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> the Place is moderately populous, Markets well ſtor'd with Fiſh, and Fleſh, both reaſonable: The People, both at Land and Sea, are not at all like the
<hi>Hollanders,</hi> who are fat, ſwinging, ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellied
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:33535:120"/>Fellows, but theſe ſmall, neat, tight, ſmart Lads, and the beſt Sea-men for Fighting and Privateering of all the <hi>Seven Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces;</hi> they are indeed true bred Sea-Rats; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſail more in the Merchant Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, theſe in the States, and in Capers.</p>
            <p>Here is a good handſome <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> an old Piece; the People here are more reſerv'd, or rather more melancholick than in other
<hi>Provinces;</hi> and the Magiſtrates are very ſevere in puniſhing lew'd Women, and Men, eſpecially the firſt, which makes them very cloſe and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate in their Amorous Affairs: They are more looſe, and greater Libertines in the Places whence we came, and drink more to
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:33535:120"/>exceſs, as well as dally with Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>We hir'd a Yacht and went on board ſome of their
<hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships, a League below the Town, where we were very ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy receiv'd and entertain'd, (tho' Strangers) for all the <hi>Dutch</hi> are not ſuch very Boors as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; but they are a ſlow, heavy People (in Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but not in Induſtry) and muſt not be hector'd and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd at, but mildly and gently handled; we won upon 'em wonderfully, giving them obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Words, and uſing civil Actions, we melted them into Complaiſance (which is not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natural to them) and by ſome happy and engaging Healths which we invented, and began, <pb n="232" facs="tcp:33535:121"/>(<hi>viz.</hi> Proſperity to the State, to the Province, to the Company Trading to <hi>India,</hi> Union to the Allies, Victory to the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Downfal of <hi>France,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of Friendſhip in our own Private Society, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Wine, (of which they were liberal, even to an exceſs) we were ſoon all of a Piece, the beſt Friends in the World, nothing like us, happy mixture of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and
<hi>Dutch.</hi> We took leave in time, and had Light enough juſt to obſerve the <hi>Ramekins,</hi> ſo fam'd in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and ſo much and ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently talk'd of, being put into the Poſſeſſion of our Renown'd and Glorious Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as a Mortgage for Money lent the
<hi>States, (when Poor and <pb n="233" facs="tcp:33535:121"/>Diſtreſſed:)</hi> 'Tis an old faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd Fort, and guards the Mouth or Entrance of the River which leads to <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> and is but a ſorry feeble Thing.</p>
            <p>But thence we went to <hi>FL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHING,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fluſhing.</note> where we lay all Night, and next Morning early walk'd round all their Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are modern, ſtrong, in good repair, and command the River, and a pretty way to Sea.</p>
            <p>Here is a large old, and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great new Dock to build in, and to lay up their biggeſt Ships of War, which this Province fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes to their <hi>Quota;</hi> there were ſeveral new Frigats, and Ships of great Force on the Stocks, which will be ready early the next Spring: Here they build, <pb n="234" facs="tcp:33535:122"/>and hence they ſend out a great many Capers, that Plague the <hi>French,</hi> and return rich, (as they us'd to do from Us when in War with <hi>England,</hi>) they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways forty or fifty abroad; they chiefly live by that Trade, and by re-taking their own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, and Allies Ships, having Salvage for the ſame, if within the Benefit of the Law Marine, or elſe all to themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fluſhing</hi> is a fine City and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Port, one of the Cautionary Places deliver'd to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> It ſtands at the Mouth of the River <hi>Scheld,</hi> where is a very convenient Haven, but a League from <hi>Middleburg,</hi> which is big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than this, but not ſo popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: Here are a great many Fiſher-Boats and ſmall Craft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:33535:122"/>to both Places, but moſt to this: Hence is the Paſſage to <hi>Flanders,</hi> whoſe Banks are in ſight, and
<hi>Bruges</hi> is but twenty-two Miles off.</p>
            <p>This is the Key of the Sea of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and is a handſome, cleanly, well-built Place, but not very modern: It was (in vain) attempted by the Dukes of <hi>Alva</hi> and <hi>Palma,</hi> but now thought almoſt impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: This poor <hi>Province</hi> has been mightily expos'd to Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and been almoſt ruin'd by thoſe prodigious ones, <hi>An.</hi>
1304, and 1509.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TERVEER</hi> is the next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Town,<note place="margin">Yerveer.</note> to which we went, and where we made but a ſhort ſtay, it being far inferior <pb n="236" facs="tcp:33535:123"/>to the t'other two, tho' this is the Third in the <hi>Province,</hi> the reſt being but inconſiderable, and rather Villages.</p>
            <p>Here is a good <hi>Stadthouſe,</hi> and and a good Church or two; the Houſes are older, and nothing near ſo Magnificent as in the t'other two Towns; nor is their Commerce to be compar'd, tho' they have a Snack in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company's Stock, and have ſome other ſmall Trade, and ſome Fiſhermen.</p>
            <p>King <hi>William,</hi> as Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> poſſeſſes moſt of the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Baronies in this
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Odyke</hi> ſome of the reſt, who keeps a kind of a Court, and makes ſome ſmall Figure when at <hi>Middleburg;</hi> we viſited his Palace, which ſtands <pb n="237" facs="tcp:33535:123"/>pleaſantly, but affords no extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Remarks. The Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther began to be cold, ſome Snow fell, and Ice was fear'd, which would have pent us in this famous Iſland, (which has fifteen or ſixteen little ones with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it) ſo we reſolv'd to take our Leaves of it; and accordingly took Boat for <hi>Hevoet ſluice,</hi> where we arriv'd in a lucky Minute, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Packet-Boat being within two Hours after to ſail, and had a very fair Gail pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; ſo we went aſhoar, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd our ſelves, bought Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions good ſtore, (there being no Halfway-Houſe at Sea,) and laid in ſome good old Hock and Brandy, and ſo embark'd about nine that Morning, and next Morning early landed at <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> 
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:33535:124"/>(being glad we were once more got on <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ground, in our Opinion, the beſt in the World,) where we reſted a few Hours, took Coach, and came to
<hi>Colcheſter,</hi> where we lay that Night, and furniſh'd our ſelves with Eringo, or Sea Holy-Root canded, (and the beſt done in
<hi>England,</hi>) at four Shillings the Pound, and fill'd our Bellies with large, fat, white, firm Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and bought ſome to bring home; and next Day in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, being the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1695, arriv'd ſafe and ſound in <hi>London,</hi> whence we had been abſent three Months and five Days.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:33535:124"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE Reports of divers Special Caſes in the Courts of
<hi>Common-Pleas</hi> and <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> in the Reign of King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Second. By Sir <hi>Thomas Jones,</hi> Knight, late Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Common-Pleas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> Sam. Keble, <hi>and Sold by</hi> A. Boſvile, <hi>at the</hi> Dial <hi>over-againſt St.</hi> Dunſtan<hi>'s Church in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</p>
            <p>AN Help and Exhortation to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicating: Or, a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe deſcribing the Meaning, Worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, Duty, and Benefits of the <hi>Holy Sacrament.</hi> And Anſwering the <hi>Doubts</hi> of
<hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>other Reaſons,</hi> which moſt generally detain Men from it. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuitable <hi>Devotions</hi> added. By
<hi>John Kettlewell,</hi> late Vicar of <hi>Coles-Hill</hi> in
<hi>Warwickſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sold by</hi> Alexander Boſvile, <hi>at the</hi> Dial,
<hi>over-againſt St.</hi> Dunſtan<hi>'s Church in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
